<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Foure sermons preached at the court vpon seuerall occasions, by the late reuerend and learned diuine, Doctor Senhouse, L. Bishop of Carlile</title>
            <author>Senhouse, Richard, d. 1626.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1627</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 179 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 74 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A11918</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 22230</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S117131</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99852346</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99852346</idno>
            <idno type="VID">17662</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A11918)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 17662)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1257:10)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Foure sermons preached at the court vpon seuerall occasions, by the late reuerend and learned diuine, Doctor Senhouse, L. Bishop of Carlile</title>
                  <author>Senhouse, Richard, d. 1626.</author>
                  <author>Blechynden, Thomas.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 141, [3] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed [by Humphrey Lownes] for R. Dawlman, at the signe of the Bible neere the great Conduit in Fleet-streete,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1627.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Editor's preface signed: Thomas Blechynden.</note>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>The last leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:17662:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:17662:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>FOVRE SERMONS PREACHED AT THE COVRT VPON ſeuerall occaſions, BY THE LATE RE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>VEREND AND LEAR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NED DIVINE, DOCTOR SENHOVSE, L. Biſhop of Carlile.</p>
            <figure>
               <head>AVSPICANTE DEO</head>
            </figure>
            <p>LONDON, Printed for <hi>R. Dawlman,</hi> at the Signe of the Bible neere the great Conduit in Fleet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreete. 1627.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:17662:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:17662:2"/>
            <head>A iuſt defence of the late L. Biſh. of Carliles <hi>honour, ſent to the iudicious Reader.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hoſe ancient Fathers, on whom came daily<note n="a" place="margin">2. Cor. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>1.28.</note> 
               <hi>the care of all the Churches,</hi> ſeeme no way better to perfect, no way ſo wel to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuate that vniuerſall care, as by wakening mens conſciences with their quills,<note n="b" place="margin">Vid. T. Liv. l. 5. c. 47.</note> whoſe wat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chings ſaued the Capitoll, and<note n="c" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Clem. Alex. l. 1. ſtrom. <hi>Euangelizo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nu &amp; ſcriptio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne, &amp;c.</hi> 1. Rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nold. l. de Rom. eccleſ. idol. <hi>Antipater cala mo vociferans</hi> Cael. l. 19. c. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>5.</note> ſpeaking with their pennes vnto the whole Church; by cauſing their ſanctified Labours, trauell, like ſo many holy pilgrims, to the liuing after their death, and in obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to our Sauiours command,<note n="d" place="margin">Mark. 16.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>Goe,</hi> euen thus vpon their very hands, <hi>into all the world to preach the Goſpel;</hi> that ſo by a ſtrange kinde of midwifrie, they may aſſiſt at the new birth of many thouſand ſoules they neuer knew, giue a ſpirituall deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance to many members of the Church they neuer ſaw, after their owne bodies are gone downe with hope into the chambers of the graue, &amp; thoſe taber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacles of fleſh reſolued into ſacred duſt; duſt that lies expecting glory. Now that this religious inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of ſpreading himſelf into a Catholique good,
<pb facs="tcp:17662:3"/> and communicating the diffuſiue bleſſings of God, and great meaſures of his Grace vnto poſteritie, li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued in the late Lord Biſhop of Carlile, Doctor <hi>Senhouſe</hi> that was—I am vnto you an vnworthy witneſſe, and yet a witneſſe; who preſume not to giue any other attribute to that neuer ſufficiently honoured Name, all attributes that can fall from my dwarft expreſsion, falling beneath thoſe tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcendent parts, thoſe vnparalleld gifts, thoſe accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mulated heapes of worth, which lodg'd in Doctor <hi>Senhouſe;</hi> to whoſe<note n="d" place="margin">Vir calamo potens &amp; viri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis eloquentiae Hieronymus. <hi>Verul. hiſt. vit. &amp; mort. l. 1.</hi>
               </note> maſculine and ſoule-begetting diſcourſes, I had the happineſſe of many yeeres acceſſes; and in his later times heard him often to my comfort profeſſe, and I neuer heard him but to my comfort, that his Lectures on King <hi>Dauids</hi> firſt and ſecond Pſalmes, were by himſelfe (for who elſe could doe it?) perfected for the preſſe; that ſo what was his Maieſties in the dutie of his originall ſeruice,<note n="f" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Clem. Alex. l. 1. Strom.</note> thoſe children of his ſoules beſt ſtrength, might now, when it ceaſeth to be with him after the manner of men, inherit the fauour of kiſsing that great <hi>Maſters</hi> ſacred hand, and liuing in his Royall heart too, and in the harts of other Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans. And therefore being caſually enformed by a friend, that ſome Sermons of his Lordſhips, had more than ſeene the Preſſe, were ready to be prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched againe to as many as would<note n="g" place="margin">Prou. 23.23.</note> 
               <hi>buy the truth;</hi>
               <note n="h" place="margin">Cyprianus quotidie Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tullianum lege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ret, notario Paulo dicens, da magiſtrum. <hi>Hieron. cat. vir. illuſt.</hi>
               </note> Saint <hi>Cyprian</hi> call'd not oftner for his learned-ſtrong-phras'd<note n="i" place="margin">Tertullianus homo doctiſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus—haereti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corum errores fortiter contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uit. <hi>Trith. l. de ſcript. eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſt.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Tertullian,</hi> than I enquired with di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence, for this my iudicious Chriſtian <hi>Gamaliel;</hi> at whoſe reuerent feete I often ſate, and learned to ſpeake by ſilence; and now began to comfort that
<pb facs="tcp:17662:3"/> loſſe with this freſh hope, that as<note n="k" place="margin">Dixit Chryſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomus ſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cionare noſſe, quod D. Pau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum quotidie manu verſaret. <hi>Keck. eccleſ. rhet. l. 2. c. 3.</hi>
               </note> S. <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> attained to an admired excellency of preaching, by hauing the great Doctor of the Gentiles, bleſſed <hi>Paul,</hi> alwayes in his hand; ſo I might improue that gift to a conſcionable diſcharge of my duty, by laying the laborious workes of this<note n="l" place="margin">Saluianus to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius orbis Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiani magiſter. <hi>Ritterſhuſ. vit. Saluian.</hi>
               </note> Maſter-Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher, a Preacher that had<note n="m" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Greg. Nazianz. ep. 140 <hi>Romani voca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bant Proareſium</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Creſſol. theat. rhet. l. 1. c 9.</note> a royaltie of ſpeech, and commanded all mens attentions, euer before mine eyes. But when I opened this booke with that reuerence which belonged vnto his name, and read with greedineſſe a line, a leafe, or two, and more; I found the order of his worke ſo inuerted, the periods in ſome places ſo vnperfected, the ſenſe by thoſe periods ſo diſioynted, the Greeke here and there where the ſenſe was good, ſo negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently, that I doe not ſay ignorantly, corrupted, and the entire frame ſo ſtript of thoſe acceſsions vpon the by, which would haue giuen much ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction to this learned age, the more learned, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he once was in it; that whereas<note n="n" place="margin">Baſil. Mag, ep. 1.</note> Saint <hi>Baſil</hi> knew <hi>Nazianzenes</hi> Epiſtles, as men know the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of their friends, by their likeneſſe to their fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers; theſe ſeemed in many things ſo vnlike that Reuerend Father, whoſe name they beare, that at the firſt ſight I hardly knew them to bee his. But when I viewed once, and againe<note n="o" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Baſil. Mag. ep. 41.</note> theſe images of his ſoule, though in ſome places too much ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowed, in ſome places much defaced, in many pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces ſet to a falſe light; yet my memorie perſwaded mine eyes, that they were copies drawne from his originals. And leaſt, induced by the like reaſons, you might ſuſpect them to be ſome ſpurious ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſititious
<pb facs="tcp:17662:4"/> pieces chriſtened with his Name, to giue them a fairer entertainement in the world and your good opinion; I craued ſo much leaue from Authoritie, as to prefixe this Epiſtle, and to let you know they are indeed his; but ſo his, as a man that's rob'd and wounded, &amp; hath his tongue taken out, is himſelfe: For firſt, they want that which could beſt ſpeake them his, that which next the efficacious cooperating of GODS Spirit with his owne, was the ſoule of euery Sermon, the ſtrong and powerfull elocution of his diuiner Tongue; and this they muſt for euer want. Next, they are wounded many wayes; wounded grama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tically in the words, wounded logically in the methode, and wounded intellectually in the ſenſe; wounds which might eaſily haue been cured by his owne preſcripts. Laſtly, they are rob'd of thoſe many rich apparellings, with which they might haue been compleately furniſht too, out of his owne Wardrope, and ſhall be ſupplyed in the next Impreſsion, and thoſe wounds ſome way healed by him, who hauing, with much difficultie, obtai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned his owne Originals of theſe foure Sermons, will ſtudy nothing more in them, than the glory of his mercifull GOD, the ſeruice of his Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique Church, the honour of his Reuerend friend, and the ſatisfaction of his iudicious Reader.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Thomas Blechynden.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:17662:4"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Revel. 2. verſ. 10. the laſt words.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>And J will give thee a Crowne of life.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>F all other things a gift the ſweeteſt, of all gifts a Crowne the greateſt, of all Crownes the Crown of life the deareſt: So as this Text comming thus with a Gift, and that gift a Crowne, and that Crowne a Crowne of life, without any curioſities of forme, the verie bare materials heere, may well now make it welcome, yea thrice welcome, as pregnant here with ſo many choiſe particulars, of Gift, of Crowne, of Life: <hi>And I will give thee a Crowne of life.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To make it yet more welcome to you, the Text (if you pleaſe) might be chriſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, and accordingly be redu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:17662:5"/> unto theſe three heads: 1. The royall excellencie of the gift, <hi>A Crowne of life.</hi> 2. The ſingular ſupremacie of the giver, <hi>I; I will give it.</hi> 3. The requiſite qualitie of the receiver, <hi>Thee:</hi> Thou that art faithfull unto death, to thee will I give the Crowne of life. But as beſide the loaden Waines, we ſee the ſingle eares of corne to be alſo glea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned; and in broken meat, the verie frag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments are alſo to be gathered up, that no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing be loſt: as in pure gold the very fy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings off are weighed, and in a chaine every little linke, everie particular pearle is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious; So everie the leaſt word herein, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing dogmatically full, as <hi>Baſil</hi> elſewhere ſpeakes, ſo loaden here with ſpirituall graine, and food, and treaſure, that (as <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtin</hi> ſayes of the 87. Pſalme, Paucitie in words, and ponderoſity in ſentences) eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie word herein hath it weight in the bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lance of the Sanctuary, and ſo, ſo manie words ſo manie worthie conſiderations, like thoſe ſheepe in the Canticles, none be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing barren amongſt them. Wee'l fancie now no other order of the words, but on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly follow on the words in this their owne order; and firſt of the firſt here, <hi>And: And I
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:17662:5"/> will give thee a Crowne of life.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>And.</hi> As St. <hi>Bartholmew</hi> is by <hi>Dionyſius</hi> quoted to have ſaid of Divinity, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>&amp; magnam eſſe &amp; minimam,</hi> that it was both great &amp; little; ſo this ſame <hi>And</hi> here, though little in the ſentence, yet great in ſenſe: me thinkes, like that <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> in St. <hi>Iames,</hi> the Helme, which though it bee ſmall, yet turneth about the whole ſhip: as a droppe, a pearle indeede, and yet a chaine of pearle too, connecting here to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether mans duety, <hi>Be faithfull,</hi> and Gods bounty, <hi>I will give thee.</hi> As if on theſe two, <hi>officium &amp; beneficium,</hi> hung all the Law and the Prophets, as <hi>Gregory</hi> ſpake elegant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of Chriſt, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, that he ioyned heaven and earth together as with a bridge; this <hi>And</hi> here being a coniunction of both, ſtanding here like <hi>Iacobs</hi> ladder upon the earth, <hi>Be ye faithfull;</hi> and the toppe of it reaching up to heaven, <hi>The Crowne of life.</hi> Or as hee wittily called the circle of the Moone <hi>Iſthmus,</hi> an Iland twixt eternity and generation: this little <hi>And</hi> here, like a little Iland, on the one hand bordering upon the Church militant, on the other upon the Church triumphant, conioyning
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:17662:6"/> here to mans Chriſtian practice of being faithfull, Chriſts gracious <hi>And</hi> of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe,
<q>And I will giue thee a Crowne of life.</q>
            </p>
            <p>That as vaine is their preſumption, who putting aſunder theſe whom God hath thus ioyned together, thus handfaſt, as I may ſpeake; as if this here were an entire propoſition, and not in compoſition: that which here is true in compounded ſenſe, they catch hold of in ſenſe divided; and ſo as when <hi>Severian</hi> once ſaid to <hi>Serapion,</hi> If <hi>Serapion</hi> dye a Chriſtian, Chriſt was not made man; <hi>Serapion</hi> thereupon accuſed him for ſaying abſolutely, Chriſt was not made man. That which here is propoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded conditionally, they preſume vpon ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutely, and ſo make reckoning to goe up to heaven in ſome whirl-wind; or as paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſengers at Sea, bee brought to the haven e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven ſleeping: to winne heaven without working, to be crown'd without ſtriving, laying claime to this obligation, without looking ever to its condition; not ſo well adviſed as the tempting Lawyer, <hi>Maſter, what ſhall I doe to inherite eternall life?</hi> But as the Lillies clothed without ſpinning, &amp;
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:17662:6"/> the fowles fed without ſowing, they will be ſaved without doing, crowned with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out caring; as if this <hi>And</hi> here like <hi>Dagons</hi> hand, might bee cut off upon the thre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhold, omitted in the entrance: ſo deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate is their deiection, who murmure as in <hi>Malachy, It is in vaine to ſerve God, and what profit is it that wee have kept his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements?</hi> Why yes, as <hi>Paul</hi> ſpake in an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other caſe, much every way: Ye ſhall not ſerve God for nought; not a cup of cold water given ſhall loſe his reward: God is not unfaithfull, that your workes of faith and labour, of love and patience, of hope ſhould bee fruſtrate. Then bee not weary of well doing, ſeeing in due ſeaſon ye ſhall reap if ye faint not, but be aboun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding alwaies in the worke of the Lord, foraſmuch as you know, your labour is not in vaine in the Lord: As God ſaid to <hi>Cain, If thou doe well, ſhalt thou not bee accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted?</hi> Doe well and have well, doe this and live, beleeve and be ſaved, be religious and reigne, be faithfull and be crowned:
<q>And I will give thee a Crowne of life.</q>
            </p>
            <p>A gracious covenant ſure; but as when the Prophet told <hi>Ahab</hi> of victory, By
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:17662:7"/> whom, ſaid hee, by whom is this to bee made good unto us? Why <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, as they wont to ſay. As the Tragedians in their arduent iſſues, were feine to fetch a god out of the engine, and to preſent him <hi>non in ſcaena ſed in ſublimi:</hi> and tis naturall, yee know, for men in miſery and extre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity to looke up, not to Court or Capi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toll, but to Heaven and call God to wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe; and familiar was it with the Anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ents, and ſo with Chriſt to pray in moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines and high places, as having their helpe from on high. And if I liſt inſert the Friers narration of Miters like Biſhops heads comming downe with haile and raine, how-ever the relation were ridicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous, his application were religious, <hi>Non eſt poteſtas niſi à Deo: Non eſt cujuſ vis,</hi> This is not every mans, not any mans part to act; not Popes for all his keyes, or pick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>locks rather: but his that hath the keyes of <hi>David,</hi> opening and no man ſhutting; his, who is Prince of the Kings of the earth, by whom Kings reigne; I that am <hi>Alpha</hi> and <hi>Omega,</hi> the firſt and the laſt; I, I will give it: Emphatically, I, ay, and excluſively I too, I and I onely will give it. As thoſe lil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:17662:7"/> for Armes of the Chriſtian King, and oyle for his Coronation, are voyced to have come downe from Heaven; and our Kings titles in ſpight of <hi>Bartholdus,</hi> runne graciouſly <hi>Dei gratiâ;</hi> and of all other Kings, good Kings, are by the very Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then <hi>Homer,</hi> ſtiled as comming downe from <hi>Iupiter;</hi> everie good gift and everie perfect, having being from above, &amp; com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming downe from the Father of lights, as S. <hi>Iames</hi> ſayes. Chriſt, ſayes <hi>Ierome,</hi> who as father of lights, cald his Diſciples the light of the world, and is there cald Father of lights, ſayes <hi>Fulgentius,</hi> and in <hi>Eſay</hi> everla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting Father, He, he it is ſhal give it. World<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly men (as <hi>Luther</hi> ſaid well) <hi>à tempore ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bent quae habent, nihil ab aeternitate vultus Dei,</hi> as their affections are ſet all on tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral things, ſo make they account to have all their turnes ſerved; not from any light of Gods countenance, but countenance of the time: and ſo Time-ſervers as they are, as <hi>Tertullian</hi> of old taxed the Gentils, <hi>majori formidine Caeſarem obſervatis quàm Iovem,</hi> that they were more obſervant of <hi>Caeſar</hi> than <hi>Iupiter;</hi> not <hi>diviſum imperium,</hi> they doe not ſo much as divide with God, but are
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:17662:8"/> 
               <hi>Caeſars</hi> by whole ſale, in religion, in reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, in ſenſe, in ſoule; ſoule and bodie and all <hi>Caeſars:</hi> and ſo ſay as hee of his Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tron, <hi>Ille mihi ſemper Deus;</hi> or as ſhee in <hi>Hoſea,</hi> aſcribe all to lovers and friends, making fleſh their arme; or as tis the Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophers character, to expect all from themſelves: they boaſt themſelves, as in <hi>Amos,</hi> of getting by their owne ſtrength, and with their owne arme, of cunning to carve for themſelves, and to deale them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves a good game, to hammer out their own happineſſe; like the Spider, climbing by thred of her own weaving, with Mot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to accordingly, <hi>Mihi ſoli debeo;</hi> in their au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit ſtanding only indebted to themſelves, ſacrificing to their owne nets, and burning incenſe to their owne yarne; Idolaters <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o all of ſecondary cauſes, and doe not ſay in their hearts, <hi>It is the Lord.</hi> Yea but this is the Lords doing: as <hi>David</hi> ſpake, Whom have wee in heaven but him? and none in the earth to bee deſired with him. And what tenure ſo happy as this of a good Chriſtian? which how-ever it enter <hi>per virgam,</hi> yet it holds <hi>in capite;</hi> holds of him who giveth more abundantly than other
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:17662:8"/> Lords take. That, as <hi>Eccleſiaſtes</hi> ſaies, unto the place from whence the rivers come, thither they returne again; unto him from whom this <hi>Crowne</hi> comes ought it alwaies to reflect againe; like the Doves, who at every graine they picke, looke upward, as giving thankes: And as <hi>Tertullian</hi> notes, that when wee pray, <hi>Thy Kingdome come, Illi deputamus, quod ab illo expectamus,</hi> wee expreſſe that of him, which wee ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect from him; a Kingdome, a Crowne. For if, as <hi>Bernard</hi> ſaid, <hi>Totum me debeo pro me facto,</hi> man owes God his whole ſelfe for creating him; what does he owe him then for this his crowning? If as <hi>P. Martyr</hi> wrote once to Queene <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> Kings be doubly bound to ſerve God; both as they are men, and as they are Kings: If the obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation ſo be doubled in regard of the live<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lihood of earthly kingdomes, how is it then multiplyed in reference to this Crowne of life? Then what will yee ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der unto the Lord for all his benefits to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards you, but take the cup of ſalvation, and call upon the Name of the Lord? In ſolemnities under the Law, they wont to take the cup &amp; drinke, in token of thankſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giving;
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:17662:9"/> other cups (no doubt) will anon bee ſtirring enough, even flagons of wine in this day of our King, as <hi>Hoſea</hi> ſpake; but take ye the cup of thankſgiving unto him, who giveth this Crowne of life,
<q>And I will give thee a Crowne of life.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Yea but ſoft and faire, leſt our gratitude fore-run the gift; this may ſeeme to ſmell of Court indeede, to give thankes for that we yet have not: Is there any ſuch haſte of performing thankfulneſſe preſent, for that benefit which is onely promiſed in the fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, <hi>I will give thee?</hi> Every promiſe that's made is not kept <hi>de facto,</hi> ay, and <hi>de jure</hi> too; <hi>Licet plura polliceri, quàm praeſtare poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſis,</hi> is the Politiques rule: promiſe does not ever beget performance; as <hi>Livie</hi> ſaid of <hi>Hanniball,</hi> that hee never ſtood to his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, but when t'was for his profit. <hi>Polli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citis dives quilibet eſſe poteſt;</hi> even the poo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt may promiſe; or if you will, it wants not authority to ſay, Great men make pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes, &amp; mean men keep them: promiſes being things which tye the multitude, which great Ones, as lightly, as <hi>Sampſon</hi> did the withes, can knap aſunder; Words of good breeding, ſay they, promiſes in
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:17662:9"/> complement, as they call it, being no obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gations. And as <hi>Antigonus</hi> was called <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon,</hi> in the future, as being ever about to give, never giving: how many <hi>Doſons</hi> know we to feede their priſoners of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe with future promiſes, as <hi>Ephraim</hi> with winde? Alchymiſts, whoſe promiſes are gold, payment but droſſe; putting off, as the tricke is, either with improbable re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſions, or promiſes of promiſes, or as their promiſes are moſt of them reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled to the Devills <hi>omnia dabo,</hi> the moſt of them imaginary and deluſory; whilſt their patients, like that man of many yeeres infirmity in the Goſpell, fainting by the poole and none to put him in, lye lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhing at hopes Hoſpitall; like a hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry man dreaming of meat, and when hee awaketh his ſoule is empty; like men in a ſwoune, cheered with ſome holy water, they revive onely to be-weary their eyes with further expectation, and to witneſſe the fallibility of promiſe. As that, mee thinkes, he may paſſe for a wiſe man in his generation, who ſaid, Were the world in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>debted to him for praiſe, he would quit it for the moyty, on condition it might bee
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:17662:10"/> paid him aforehand; and ye ſay, A bird in the hand is worth two in the buſh: <hi>Nihil putant utile niſi quod manibus teneri poteſt,</hi> as <hi>Lactantius</hi> ſpake; counting nothing profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table that is not preſent: <hi>Blanda praeſentia,</hi> as <hi>Hilary</hi> ſpake, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, as <hi>Nyſſen,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, as <hi>Philo;</hi> Men ſet the gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land all on things preſent, liſtning more to ſenſe about things preſent, than to faith about things to come; ſo accuſtomed to the common fallacy of putting more into premiſes, than is commonly found in the concluſion: as that wee will hardly take even Gods word without a pawne; as he well exclaimed, <q>
                  <l>O caecos animos, Chriſto diffidimus omnes,</l>
                  <l>Cum tamen inveniat praedo vel ipſe fidem.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>How-ever it fare ſo in mens promiſes, of little truſt farther than ſight, their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crees upon new importunities cancelled, their determinations upon new reſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons inconſtant, their promiſes upon new conſiderations ebbing into emptineſſe, as eaſily changed as when a tune is changed upon an inſtrument of muſique; chang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing oftner than <hi>Laban</hi> changed <hi>Iacobs</hi> wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges; as <hi>Tertullian</hi> ſpake of the Peacock, all
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:17662:10"/> in changeable colours, as often chang'd as moved: Italians all, as <hi>Aeneas Sylvius</hi> ſaid of Italy, <hi>Novitate quadam nihil habet ſtabile,</hi> ſo mutable, they have nothing ſtable, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe nor other. Beſides, as hee well obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, wee can hardly without offence, put great Ones in mind of their promiſes; yet 'tis a boldneſſe God likes well enough, to preſſe him with his promiſes; that hath God ſaid it, and ſhall hee not doe it? hath he ſpoken it, and hath he not accompliſht it? Many devices, ſaies <hi>Salomon,</hi> are in a mans heart, but the counſell of the Lord ſhall ſtand: the things exhibited to us by God, as wealth, health, honour, may fade and faile; but the things thus promiſed us by him ſhall never faile. As <hi>Ioſhua</hi> rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon'd, Nothing hath failed of all the good things which the Lord your God promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed you; nothing hath failed, neither ſhall faile. So this is no vaine word concerning you. As old <hi>Sarah</hi> laughed at hearing of childe-bearing, no doubt, the carnall infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delity of ſuch as never taſted of any pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of the world to come, laugh now in their ſleeves, to heare talk thus of Crowns to be given to ſilly men. But as <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaks,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:17662:11"/> we know whom we have beleeved; and future here if it be, ſo certaine it is, a man may lay his life on't, that hee who ſaid it, will doe it, will give it:
<q>And I will give thee a Crowne of life.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Will give thee.</hi> Why then if there be anie thing freer than gift, let the impudent Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſt here ſtand up with his <hi>debitum ut do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num:</hi> Eternall life (ſayes their <hi>Andradius</hi>) not ſo much a gratuitie of liberalitie from God, as a due to good workes; heaven be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing as due to good workes, as hell to ill, as ſillily ſayes <hi>Andradius, Coſter,</hi> and the Rhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſts: or if yet they want ſome, fetch they in <hi>Bellarmines</hi> tower, his Babell of merits, <hi>Paradiſum ex merito, &amp;c.</hi> ſayes he, even Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>radiſe being to be purchaſed by merit. <hi>O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pera bona mercatura regni coeleſtis,</hi> are his owne words; as if by good workes a man might chaffer for heaven, and buy this Crowne: who as they dare trade and bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter about ſale of worldly kingdomes, ſo venture they to truck and traffick about ſale of heavenly Crownes too, having coi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned a money of merit to buy it with. <hi>Non ſolùm ex merito Chriſti, ſed etiam ex merito ſuo;</hi> ſo <hi>Bellarmine.</hi> As when musk is min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gled
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:17662:11"/> with amber-greaſe, as <hi>Gomezius</hi> thinks, he ſubtilly compoundeth them: So farre from counting it thus a gift, as that <hi>Vega,</hi> a Clerke of theirs, durſt inſolently ſay, <hi>Gratis non accipiam,</hi> That this Crown which coſt the Martyrs ſo much, he would not take it of free gift, not bee beholding to God for beſtowing it, not accept of it if it coſt him nought. And ſo <hi>Coſter, Noluit Chriſtus, &amp;c.</hi> that Chriſt would not have this Crowne given us <hi>gratis, ſed meritis noſtris:</hi> as hee in <hi>Xenophon</hi> ſaid, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, they coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting ſo this Crowne rather for a bootie than a gift. Yea but ſayes <hi>Heſychius,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, Heaven is not ſo the wage of ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants workes, but the bounty of their Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters gift; who is no Merchant, ſaid <hi>Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius</hi> well; <hi>Donator non venditor,</hi> as <hi>Philo: Beneficia dedit non vendidit,</hi> ſayes <hi>Bernard,</hi> Gods good turnes they are given not ſold, and this kingdom not <hi>partum,</hi> but <hi>paratum,</hi> a kingdome not purchaſed by us, but pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared for us, <hi>Matth.</hi> 25. And all that ſhall thus be crowned, <hi>filii divini beneficii,</hi> as <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtin</hi> calls them, children of the divine kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe: by grace ſaved through faith, &amp; that not of your ſelves, it is the gift of God, as
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:17662:12"/> 
               <hi>Paul</hi> evidently ſpeaketh. The worth of this Crowne being ſo infinitely above all price of humane performance, that ſaies <hi>Anſelmus, Si homo mille annis ſerviret, &amp;c.</hi> Suppoſe a man ſhould ſerve God zealouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly a thouſand yeeres here, yet ſhould hee not thereby deſervedly merit to bee one halfe day in heaven: And; <hi>Et ſi millies mori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amur, &amp;c.</hi> ſaies <hi>Chryſoſtome,</hi> Though wee ſhould dye a thouſand deaths, and doe all vertuous exploits, all would be of no con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignity to this Crowne: thoſe being one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly waies to the Kingdome, not cauſes of reigning; meanes by, but not cauſes why: though <hi>ſecundùm opera,</hi> yet not <hi>propter ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra;</hi> So <hi>Gregory:</hi> though <hi>propter promiſſum,</hi> yet not <hi>propter commiſſum;</hi> So <hi>Anſtin:</hi> not <hi>factum,</hi> but <hi>pactum.</hi> And if the excellency of <hi>Iacob</hi> was not worthy the leaſt of Gods mercies ſhewed him, <hi>Geneſ.</hi> 32. well may the houſe of <hi>Iacob</hi> now confeſſe, <hi>Non dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitate noſtrâ, ſed dignitate tuâ.</hi> And not to dwell longer in the plaine, take the adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries that cold comfort from <hi>Auſtin</hi> for concluſion; Never ſhall they come in the heavenly Ieruſalem, who doe not from their hearts profeſſe, that the comming
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:17662:12"/> thither is not <hi>proprij operis,</hi> but <hi>Domini mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neris;</hi> not by their owne behaviour, but Gods favour: <hi>Non meritis operantis,</hi> but <hi>mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeratione donantis,</hi> Not by the merits of the worker, but by the mercy of the giver, crowning his owne gift, not our workes; ſaving us, not out of merit, but with mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy and compaſſions, as <hi>David</hi> ſpeaketh. That whatſoever baſe ſpirits of deluſion, creeping into houſes, and leading captive ſilly women, whiſper unto others; ſay ye of this Crowne, as <hi>Rahel</hi> did of children, Give mee it, or elſe I die: Without this Crowne bee given us, wee are but dead men; that, as ſpake the woman <hi>Iohn</hi> 4. Sir, give mee this water, Lord, give us this Crowne of life.</p>
            <p>In ſpight of inſolency and error both, give it then hee will; but to whom trow ye? The covenant here runnes not with a <hi>Noverint univerſi,</hi> to All, All; but <hi>Omnibus Chriſti fidelibus,</hi> To thee, thou faithfull ſoule, to thee will I give it: not <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, as <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> well handles giving, not hand o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver head, at random, at all adventures; like thoſe men, who, as hee ſpake, <hi>projiciunt
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:17662:13"/> magis quàm dant,</hi> rather throw away than give; and, <hi>Perdere ſciunt, donare neſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unt,</hi> They know how to loſe, but not how to give; as he ſaid of <hi>Alexander,</hi> that hee would have given away Cyprus for a ſong, Phoenicia for a verſe; like <hi>Herods</hi> halfe kingdome: nay that head which was worth more than his whole kingdome, given away for a gig, a daunce; and ſo their gifts, ſo ill placed, procure more ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred than love. And as the Iewes wittily uſe to ſay, looke what is ſo given, tis writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten in the Harts horne, ſo mew'd, caſt e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very yeere, as that ever and anon yee may goe ſeeke it; and ſo nothing that brands many men with more indiſcretion, than the ill diſpoſing of their gifts. God here gives not ſo, by chance but choice; and this Crowne of life the Lord hath promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to them that love him, ſaith St. <hi>Iames,</hi> them that love his appearing, ſaies S. <hi>Paul,</hi> to be given them for whom it is prepared, <hi>Matth.</hi> 20. Not as they ſpake of <hi>Gedeons</hi> brethren, Every one like the children of a King; Not every one, but ſome choiſe ones, heires of that kingdome, as St. <hi>Iames</hi>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:17662:13"/> calls them; Heads deſtinated to the Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem, as <hi>Tertullian.</hi> 'Tis true, God makes his Sunne to riſe on the evill too, and ſend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth raine on the uniuſt alſo, ſo that by theſe outward things, who knoweth whether hee bee worthy love or hatred? But as <hi>Abraham,</hi> though hee gave gifts to the ſons of his concubines, <hi>Gen.</hi> 25. yet all his goods (reads one tranſlation, all he had reade we now) the heritage gave he to his <hi>Iſaac,</hi> in whom the covenant was eſtabli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed, the ſonne of promiſe; So if God of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, even unto thoſe baſtard children gives ſecular things, common gifts; yet the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance, this Crowne gives hee onely to them, who after the manner of <hi>Iſaac</hi> are children of promiſe, as <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeakes: to you his <hi>Iſaacs,</hi> his Laughters, in whom he takes pleaſure. <hi>Wee fooles</hi> (ſay they in the fift of <hi>Wiſedome) wee fooles thought his life madneſſe, and his end without honour; but how is he counted among the children of God, and his portion among the Saints?</hi> Thou that not onely (as <hi>Eccleſiaſticus</hi> ſaid) being iuſt, art one better than a thouſand others; not onely as the people ſaid of <hi>David,</hi> worth
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:17662:14"/> ten thouſands of us; but as <hi>Philo</hi> ſpake, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, equivalent not onely to a number, but a whole nation of us. Thou not only a Profeſſor, but a Protector of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion; Thou not onely faithfull, but a De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fender of the Faith; Thou that art valiant for the truth, as was written upon the ſword of <hi>Charles</hi> the Great, <hi>Decem praecep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torum cuſtos Carolus, Charles</hi> keeper of the ten Commandements: Thou man of his deſires, to thee will hee give this Crowne of life.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Give thee?</hi> What? ſome great gift ſure: for though the hide-bound world neither does, nor can give things without her owne circle, &amp; ſo pent within the ſpheare of her owne ſcant activity, is faine to give here a crab, and there a crum, and when ſhee drops a pearle, a golden apple, or ſo, that's precious: Conſider but well the hard opening of the ſhell, weigh all cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances, and they will be found but as the Phyſitians drugges, which they call <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> gifts, and yet we pay deare for them. Well, if they be penni-worths, ſure they are not gifts; yet this giver <hi>Habet quod det,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:17662:14"/> &amp; dat nemo largiùs:</hi> as the Scripture ſpeaks of <hi>Araunah,</hi> as a King gave hee unto the King; this gives like a King, not under a Crowne, gives here to a King, a Crowne; <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> indeed. Not that every crowne is ſtraight-way commendable; there be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing voluptuous crownes of Roſes, as in Wiſedome; a crowne of pride, to which a woe belongeth, <hi>Eſay</hi> 28. So Dragons &amp; Beaſts crownes in the <hi>Revelation;</hi> and ſo <hi>Corona vitioſa, ruinoſa,</hi> and the reſt, as the Poets Crownes of Laurell and Ivie, Crownes little better than the weedes which wrapt about <hi>Ionahs</hi> head, traſh of no value. Yea Crownes not onely ſo by reſemblance, but reall; and of that rank, than which this world below hath no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing higher; yet ſuch as that ſome, even the owners, who might bee bold with their owne, themſelves have ſaid, They that knew but the troubles of their cares, would not ſtoope to take up their Crownes: as <hi>Canutus</hi> ſet his Crowne up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Crucifix, Crownes having their croſſes, thiſtles in their armes, and thorns in their ſides; even Chriſts royall title (note
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:17662:15"/> ſome) having beene ſet upon the Croſſe, as much as to ſay, Kings have their croſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, yea &amp; loſſes too; &amp; if Popes, worſt Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mets to Kings, may prevaile, their hard deaths too, that being a principle of their deteſtable doctrine, <hi>Crueltie to Crownes.</hi> Yea but as Ieſus ſaid, that his Kingdome was not of this world, this is none of theſe Crownes, but a Crowne where death hath no claime, <hi>A Crowne of life.</hi> As hee that bearing three crownes, added well the word, <hi>Quarta perennis erit,</hi> that the fourth would be for ever; what-ever be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come eyther of thoſe criminall, or coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfeit, or kingly crownes, <hi>Quarta perennis,</hi> this Crowne will laſt for ever, <hi>A Crowne,</hi> or as the other Tranſlation not amiſſe, <hi>The Crowne of life.</hi> Whither at laſt being now come, as <hi>Nyſſen</hi> once, being to ſpeake of thoſe words, <hi>Our Father which art in heaven,</hi> wiſht himſelfe wings, wherewith to mount and flye a pitch proportionable to the height of the matter in hand; how could I wiſh now ſome winged ſpeech, to ſoare according to the ſublimitie of the matter? And yet even then too, as <hi>Chryſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome</hi>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:17662:15"/> ſpake, <hi>Sermo non valet exprimere, expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rimento opus eſt,</hi> Speech would not reach that excellency of it, which cannot be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed but by experience; fitter to be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeved, than poſsible to be diſcourſed, ſayes <hi>Proſper:</hi> So exceeding an eternall weight of glory, as neyther Rhetorician can di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcourſe, nor Geometrician meaſure, nor A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rithmetician number. The beautie of <hi>Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolon,</hi> to it but deformitie; the ſtrength of <hi>Sampſon,</hi> to it but infirmitie; the age of <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thuſalem,</hi> to it but mortalitie: All the mirth here, to that but penſiveneſſe; all pleaſure here, to that but heavineſſe; all ſweetneſſe here, to that but bitterneſſe: The verie Crown of reioycing, <hi>the Crowne of life.</hi> All the ſplendors here, and they are many: not as that cluſter which the ſpies brought, but only as huskes as it were of thoſe grapes of Canaan: as <hi>Ioſeph</hi> caſt chaffe downe the ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, to let the Nations know of their abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of graine; onely as chaffe to that a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundant harveſt growing in the land of promiſe, <hi>the Crowne of life.</hi> Then not to treſpaſſe further upon your patience, I only tender unto your conſideration this your
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:17662:16"/> owne Day, as ſome ſhort comment upon this laſting Crown: That as it hath ever beene the guiſe of godly men, from the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holding of worldly things to beget hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly thoughts; to turne the ſight of every ſolemnitie into a Schoole of Divinitie; and from things they ſee here downward, to make a proſpect upward: As when <hi>Ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gentius</hi> ſaw the Nobility aſſembled at Rome, the ſight of the glittering of that Court mounted his meditation to the thought of a higher Court, the heauenly Ieruſalem. From the hearing of muſique, hee is now with God, who is ſaid to have entred upon the meditation of the holy harmony in heaven: And upon ſight of ſoft clothing in Kings houſes, mee thinks wee ſhould be led to thinke of that white clothing in the Revelation, and robe of righteouſneſſe: And from your owne Crowning, thinke of this Crown of life; there will be much learned, eſpecially that which is the principall drift of the Text here, to fortifie againſt tribulations and oppoſitions for Chriſts cauſe. As <hi>David</hi> tells of crowning with favour as with a
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:17662:16"/> ſhield; this very Crowne may ſerve you as a ſhield againſt all aſſaults, the aſſurance of this Crowne a Superſedeas againſt all feare. <hi>Cùm voles omnium rerum obliviſci, co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gita Caeſarem,</hi> could <hi>Seneca</hi> ſay, Would thou forget all other things, thinke then of <hi>Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſar;</hi> but as a Chriſtian wouldſt thou for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get all worldly combrances, <hi>Cogita Coro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nam,</hi> thinke on this Crowne: and what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever the dureſſe bee, it will bee but light, if you ballance it with this weight of glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry. <hi>Exultans regno, inſultans mundo:</hi> Aſcend but now into conſideration of this Crowne, and from thence, as from ſome high mountaine, you will ſoone behold all theſe things here below, as little things, of little value, petty things, not worth your care, much leſſe your feare. Whileſt as the ſhepheard crown'd with flowres and herbes, fighting with the baſiliske, could not be hurt by reaſon of the preſervative in his garland; You ſhall tread upon the baſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lisk &amp; the aſpe, &amp; they ſhall have no pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er to hurt you, if you make uſe of the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervatives in this Crowne: For, man, haſt thou loſſe here? thou ſhalt have a gift there.
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:17662:17"/> Haſt thou contempt here? thou ſhalt have a Crowne there. Haſt thou death here? thou ſhalt have life there;
<q>And I will give thee a Crowne of life.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Which Crowne of life, after your good fight fought in this life, the Lord Ieſus give you for his mercies ſake: To whom with the Father and the holy Ghoſt be aſcribed, &amp;c.</p>
            <closer>Laus Deo.</closer>
         </div>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="27" facs="tcp:17662:17"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>GALAT. 4.16.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Am J therefore become your enemie, becauſe I tell you the truth?</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>N Argument unadviſedly choſen, (will ſome wiſe one at firſt hearing ſay) to undertake to treate of Truth, the telling wherof, your very Text aforehand tells you, procures enmity; as if wittingly you meant to run upon ſome rocke of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaſte &amp; diſpleaſure. But as <hi>Paul</hi> ſpake, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded better things of you, according to the Preachers counſell, without obſerving thoſe windes, come I now to ſow, and without thoſe cloudes to reape; and ſo I may prove true to the Text: ſhunne not though the Text prove true to me, for tel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling truth to undergoe enmity,
<q>Am I therefore become your enemy? &amp;c.</q>
            </p>
            <pb n="28" facs="tcp:17662:18"/>
            <p>As if holy <hi>Paul</hi> according to the te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of the context here, had zealouſly thus expoſtulated with that people: I have beſtow'd labour upon you, as in the 11. verſ. I have preached the Goſpell unto you, as in the 13. verſ. I have heretofore beene welcome unto you for my Miniſteries ſake, received of you as an Angell of God, in the 14. verſ. Your very eies not more precious unto you, as in the 15. verſ. And having given no cauſe (I wote of) why your good wills ſhould now be alienated from mee, unleſſe it bee for ſeeking to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claime you from erroneous doctrines of weake and beggarly rudiments, and freely and truely putting you in minde of the things that belong to your ſalvation; if that be the cauſe, what an unworthy part is it to maligne him that hath beene ſo mindefull of you, to trouble him that hath beene ſo true to you, to repay truth with enmity, to render enmity for telling truth?</p>
            <q>Am I therefore your enemie? &amp;c.</q>
            <p>From out which woufe, of Scripture, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, ſome expert workman would quickly draw many curious threds, like
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:17662:18"/> to the Spouſes lips in the Canticles, drop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping as the hony combe, from every word diſtilling pearles of precious obſervation. As firſt from the perſon here maligned, <hi>I Paul,</hi> an Apoſtle, not of men, neither by man, but by Ieſus Chriſt, and God the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: <hi>Apoſtolus per Antonomaſiam,</hi> I that la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boured more aboundantly than they all; <hi>Paul,</hi> whom to have ſeene in the Pulpit, was one of <hi>Auſtins</hi> three wiſhes, <hi>Conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſsimus gratiae Praedicator,</hi> as he ſtiles him: yet hee thus become to be held an enemy, inferres the accuſtomed lot of beſt deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving men, enmity. Next from the quarrell, here, <hi>Therefore,</hi> for telling truth to be hated, <hi>irrationabiliter malignati,</hi> as he ſpake, the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaſonable dealings of malignant men: as in the ſecond of <hi>Wiſedome, He is not for our turne, hee checketh us for offending, profeſsing to have the knowledge of God, &amp;c.</hi> There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore let us lye in waite for the righteous: Therefore let us examine him with re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bukes: Therefore. Then from the change here come to paſſe, of formerly ſuch a friend, thus to become, &amp; held an enemy. The giddy inconſtancy of the people, what
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:17662:19"/> a tickle tenure he holds by that hold of the multitude, <hi>Neutrum modò, mas modò vulgus:</hi> Hating here, whom heretofore they affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted. As ere-while in the 14. of the <hi>Acts,</hi> prone to ſacrifice to him, and by and by perſwaded to ſtone him. But diſmiſsing thoſe Minims upon the by, and aiming onely at the maine truth here, to cleare that, chuſe I hence now to preſent before you, onely theſe three eſſentially materiall meditations: The dignity of truth in it ſelfe: The indignity offred truth by others enmity: The enduring of that enmity by the tellers of truth: The high excellency of truth: The harſh entertainment of that excellency: The hearty enduring of that entertainment. For to naturalize theſe parts to the Text: As 'tis an increpation 'gainſt their bad dealing with truth, ſo <hi>de jure</hi> it magnifies verity. As 'tis an interrogation, the keeneſt forme of aſſertion, ſo <hi>de facto</hi> it certifies their enmity. As 'tis an expoſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation pregnant with firme reſolution, ſo <hi>de debito</hi> it ratifies his conſtancy: <hi>De jure</hi> truth deſerveth better; <hi>de facto</hi> it receiveth worſe: <hi>De debito,</hi> for all that worſe, we
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:17662:19"/> ought not to abandon that better, within theſe liſts limiting what now is intended to be uttered. The ſpies that can try the whole land by one cluſter, meaſure whole <hi>Hercules</hi> by a foot, diſcerne the whole web by the liſt, may ſave a labour, eaſe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves and others by departing, as <hi>Pilate</hi> when hee had asked what is truth, went out: to the honeſt hearts remaining, remain theſe in order to be ſerved in: A true valua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of truth in it ſelfe, &amp; ſo what good en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertainment it deſerveth. The undervalu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of truth 'mongſt men, and ſo what bad entertainment, enmity, it findeth. The due practice of the profeſſors of truth, whom no ſuch enmity diſcourageth from telling truth,
<q>Am I therefore become your enemy? &amp;c.</q>
            </p>
            <p>For the firſt then, the excellency of truth in it ſelfe, as we uſe to ſpeake of the end, laſt in execution, firſt in intention; Truth here in the Text, though laſt in ſituation, yet firſt in ſenſe and ſubſtance: according<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly as <hi>Plato</hi> againe and againe gives truth the leading, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, &amp;c. And hee, ſaies he, that will be happy in the end, ought to lay hold on truth in the beginning: <hi>The
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:17662:20"/> beginning of thy Word is truth,</hi> ſaies <hi>David.</hi> As 'tis ſaid, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, that of any work beginning, the forefront ought to be faire, like to that beautifull gate of the Temple. Enter wee firſt here upon the beautifull excellency of Truth, <hi>in Theſi</hi> for truth in generall, whether yee liſt conceive truth an adequation, a conformity of the thing and the underſtanding as ſome de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fine; or rather (for it is here a telling of truth) an adequation of ſpeech to the thing: Truth being in the minde as <hi>in ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jecto cognitivo,</hi> in ſpeech as <hi>in ſigno repraeſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tativo,</hi> in the minde as knowing, in the mouth as manifeſting, each way glorious things are ſpoken of Truth. Truth the meate of the minde, ſaies the <hi>Platoniſt, A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimi cibus:</hi> Truth the ſuſtenance of the ſoule, ſayes <hi>Lactantius, Animae pabulum:</hi> Truth the ſpouſe of the underſtanding, ſay others, <hi>Sponſa intellectus:</hi> Verity the virgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity of the ſoule, as falſhood the adultery. As hee ignorantly, but luckily ſaid, they were called Mechanick Arts, becauſe the underſtanding <hi>quodammodo in ijs moechatur,</hi> ſaid he, becauſe the underſtanding princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pally created for ſpirituall apprehenſions,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:17662:20"/> in thoſe arts, leaving Truth, the Spouſe of the underſtanding, adulterates, pollutes it ſelfe with corporall employments: not only Mechanicall Arts are ſuch digreſsions beſides truth; but even the moſt liberall ſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences &amp; knowledges in the world, are but as pages, torch-bearers to truth, <hi>quae etſi non ducunt, conducunt;</hi> the ſcope and concluſion of all true knowledge being Truth; &amp; the inquiſition after that concluſion, keeping the candle burning, &amp; the eies waking. And this is the unvaluable advantage, how-ever ſhallow men ſleight it, which a Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pher, a Student, a man converſing with his underſtanding, hath above other empty men of the world, that whilſt thoſe ſenſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aliſts fondly ſtand courting other vaine beauties, ſome of them it may be naturall, many of them artificiall, moſt of them naught: the Intellectualiſt the whilſt hath frequent and familiar addreſſes, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaches, acquaintance with beautifull Truth. So that of Truth we may ſay as did the Queene of Sheba of <hi>Salomon, Happy are thy men, happy are thy ſervants that ſtand continually before thee, and heare thy wiſedome,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:17662:21"/> learne thy Truth.</hi> But <hi>in Hypotheſi,</hi> for this particular truth here about ceremonies, wrigled in againe among the Galatians, and whereunto they needes againe would bee in bondage, a carriage concentrique with relapſes at this day into Papiſticall ſuperſtitions, ſaid <hi>Gualter</hi> of his time then, to bring it no neerer. Verily as <hi>Mirandula</hi> ſpake, <hi>Veritatem Philoſophia quaerit, Theolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gia invenit, Religio poſsidet,</hi> that Truth was a thing which Philoſophy ſought, Divini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty found, Religion poſſeſſed. Other truths there be, as Philoſophicall truths, which may ſo be glittering, but they are theſe di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Truths that are the glorious. Truths there bee not worth the wet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of a mans finger for, much leſſe the ſhedding of his bloud for them, as ſundry rules in ſciences, and curious arts, and mathematicall principles: Truth, the tougheſt maintaining whereof will never make a true Martyr, though ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narily ſhall yee finde more obſtinacy in maintaining thoſe petty truths, than con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancy in upholding weightier truths; and here and there ſome <hi>Heliodor,</hi> yeelding ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:17662:21"/> to be caſt out of his Biſhoprick, than to call in his bookes, though but <hi>Aethio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>picks,</hi> having not ſo much as colour of truth. And other ſorts of truth there bee publiſhed, yet ought not to bee practiſed, <hi>veritates audiendae, non imitandae,</hi> as hee ſpeakes; as politick Theorems, he that will ſpeedily thrive in ſuch and ſuch places, he muſt lye, flatter, diſſemble, and do worſe: truths which it may be ſome good man will truſt, but never try; and ſuch like o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther truths, whereof a man may ſafely be ignorant, but not ſafely practicant; that as Chriſt bid the Minſtrels, <hi>Get you hence,</hi> hence with ſuch truths: As <hi>Samuel</hi> ſaid of <hi>Iſhai's</hi> ſeven ſonnes, The Lord hath choſen none of theſe truthes; no, but as he defines Theologick truth to be the truth neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie in the voyage to ſalvation, divine truth, ſaving truth, truth reſpectively to Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; yea this is that truth of Chriſtians, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comparably fairer than <hi>Helen</hi> of the Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cians, as <hi>Auſtin</hi> ſpake, whilſt as God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe is truth and everie man a lyar, ſo are all thoſe other but as traſh to his truth, who (as one heroically ſpoke) if hee were
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:17662:22"/> to be corporeal, would ſure have Light for his bodie, and Truth for his ſoule; and ſo as he is, hath he Truth as his Vſher going before his face, as in the Pſalmiſt. And whereas of other divine attributes, ſome are eſpecially aſcribed to the Father, as om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nipotencie; ſome to the Sonne, as wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome; ſome to the holy Ghoſt, as good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe: Truth by the holy Spirit is peculi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arly attributed to them all, <hi>Lord God of Truth, Ieſus that Truth, the Spirit of Truth.</hi> Chriſt ſaith the cauſe of his comming, his errand into the world, was to beare wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe unto the truth; &amp; the Spirit of truth, not onely ſo <hi>eſſentialiter,</hi> but <hi>doctrinaliter,</hi> leading into all truth; his wayes truth, his workes truth, his word truth, all truth: who as fountaine of truth himſelfe, favou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth alſo truth in others too, giving his <hi>placet</hi> to them that ſtudie truth, <hi>Qui ſtudent veritati, placent ei: The Lords eyes are upon the truth,</hi> ſayes <hi>Ieremy;</hi> no tune more plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing to God than truth. Then come on ye that ſay, <hi>Who will ſhew us any good? Cui bono?</hi> what good ſhall we get by this your painted pearle of truth, this treaſure in a
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:17662:22"/> traunce, for all your letter of commenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of Truth, <hi>Quid mihi prodeſt cogno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcere Veritatem,</hi> as in <hi>Auſtin?</hi> Good? Why ſay what is the good you would have? Is it liberty? <hi>O bona libertas;</hi> why know the Truth, and the Truth ſhall make you free, <hi>Iohn</hi> 8. the Truth there not onely <hi>Veritas Chriſtus,</hi> but <hi>Veritas Chriſti;</hi> a Truth truely to be tearmed <hi>liberalis,</hi> not onely as liberall ſciences, becauſe they are worthy <hi>homine libero,</hi> but this alſo <hi>hominem liberat;</hi> for where the Spirit of the Lord is, there is li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty; and this is our liberty, that wee are ſubiect to that Verity, as <hi>Auſtin</hi> ſpeaketh. Or is it ſafety you ſeeke? The world's wrong, the ſureſt ſafety is not in ſubtilty; no, Truth is the Kings Guard, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, ſayes <hi>Salomon,</hi> Truth that which helpes to keep and preſerve the King, <hi>Prov.</hi> 20. yea his Truth ſhall be your ſhield and buckler, as <hi>David</hi> ſpeaketh. Is it comfort upon all oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>currences you care for? Why, it was <hi>Heze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kiah's</hi> cordiall lying ſicke, that he had walk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed before God in Truth; Truth there not oppoſite onely <hi>falſo</hi> but <hi>fucato;</hi> when hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocriſie, pollicie, fraud, falſhood, errour
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:17662:23"/> can miniſter no comfortable ingredient, in extremity, then faire fall Truth. Beyond the comforts here, is it heaven hereafter you would have hold of? Why, remember who it is ſhall dwell in Gods Tabernacle, reſt in his holy Mountaine, hee that ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the Truth in his heart: yea the bleſſed life it ſelfe is nothing elſe but <hi>gaudium de Veritate,</hi> ſaies <hi>Auſtin,</hi> a reioycing over Truth: liberty, ſafety, comfort, heaven, if all things bee worth any thing, Truth is worth them all: Truth 'tis <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, as in <hi>Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to,</hi> faire; nor painter, nor ſtatuary that can expreſſe like beauty to Truths, ſaid <hi>Phile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon:</hi> Truth 'tis <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, as in <hi>Eſdras,</hi> ſtrong; ſtrong above wine, women, king, ſtronger than all: Truth 'tis <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, as <hi>Clinias,</hi> laſting; Truth abideth, &amp; is ſtrong for ever, ſaid <hi>Zerobabel;</hi> the lip of Truth ſhall be eſtabli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed for ever, ſaid <hi>Salomon.</hi> That hence may even Nobles attend, how the Romane Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor wont alwaies to weare upon his breaſt the image of Truth, as if the trueſt enſigne of Nobility were Truth. Hence may even Senators attend, how the Egyptian Iudges wore alwaies in a chaine about their neck,
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:17662:23"/> the picture of Truth; and 'twas <hi>Iethro's</hi> counſell to <hi>Moſes,</hi> for Iudges over the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, to chooſe <hi>viros veraces,</hi> men of Truth, <hi>in quibus ſit veritas;</hi> nor could the high Prieſt give ſentence without the bleſt-plate of iudgement on, wherein they put <hi>Verita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem,</hi> as if Truth were the very forme of iudgement, what ever the matter bee. Hence may even the valiant attend, how in that whole armour of God, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 6. Truth is there put the firſt peece of the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noply, as if the principall obiect of valour were Truth, and that the prime care to have the loines girt about with Truth. O then, according to that excellent commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation <hi>Quintilian</hi> gives <hi>Veſpaſian, patientiſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus veri,</hi> that he was moſt enduring, moſt ſuffering of Truth: Suffer yee now the word of exhortation unto Truth, ye ſhall have it tendred now in no meaner termes than <hi>Solomons, Buy the Truth</hi> ('tis no Symo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie) <hi>and ſell it not;</hi> buy it of God by pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, buy it of Bookes by reading, buy it of Orthodoxe men by hearing, buy it over &amp; over, ye cannot over-buy it, <hi>Non Priamus tanti, &amp;c.</hi> Truth being as wiſedome, to be
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:17662:24"/> preferred before ſcepters and thrones, to be loved above health and beauty, preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous ſtones not to bee compared unto it, gold but as gravell in reſpect of it, and ſil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver to be counted but as clay before it, and hee to bee reckoned a wiſe Merchant that ſelleth all that he hath to buy it. I dare uſe <hi>Salomons</hi> phraſe, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the price is now in your hand, buy it: Sell it not nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for love, nor mony, nor policie, nor for no worldly payments, much leſſe for promiſes: they ſell the Truth (ſaid <hi>Lavater</hi> well) who for worldly reſpects live in ſuch places where there is no publick pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſsion of the Truth. As <hi>Eſau</hi> ſold his birth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right for a meſſe of pottage; and ſaies <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon, Pro buccellâ panis deſerit veritatem,</hi> for handfulls of barley and peeces of bread, for ſecular conſiderations they ſell the Truth; and by their leave, ſo doe they too, who living in places where the Truth is publickly profeſſed, do <hi>Iudas</hi>-like yet ſtand ready preſſed for pence, as much as in them lies to betray the Truth, or out of politique ends, to ſell the Truth, ſelling under the marke of the Beaſt, as in the <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velation;</hi>
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:17662:24"/> and for all their wiſedome in their generation, ſelling, as unthrifts doe their lands, that which they never knew the worth of, Truth: and as the Satyriſt ſpake, <hi>Vende animam lucro,</hi> ſelling their ſoules too in the bargaine and ſale of truth. Having ſold his Bible, which onely hee had then left: <hi>Now</hi> (ſaid <hi>Serapion) have I ſold that which taught me to ſell all;</hi> and hee that ſells truth, ſells that which teacheth to ſell all to buy it; and if a man could ſell truth for all the gold of <hi>India,</hi> what would it profit to winne the world and loſe the truth? Sell it not, nay, but be ye eſtabliſhed in the preſent truth, as St. <hi>Peter</hi> ſpake. And againe I ſay, be ye eſtabliſhed in the preſent truth; it is the preſent truth, and 'twas the primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Truth, when Purgatory was yet un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kindled, and Indulgences yet unhatched, when Maſſe was yet unmoulded, and Tranſubſtantiation yet unbaked, when Merits were yet unminted, and Sinnes ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niall uninvented; when Laycks of the cup were yet uncouſened, and Eccleſiaſtiques unexempted: when Popes tranſcendent power was uncreated, and depoſing of
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:17662:25"/> Kings yet undreamed of, before this <hi>Lerna</hi> lake of errors yet was congregated, before ever theſe fancies of Rome were rock'd in their cradles, was the preſent truth: And be yee eſtabliſhed in it, not tottering and wavering to and fro, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, as they that are carried about with everie wind of doctrine, but <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, ſpeaks S. <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> there, firmly ſettled, eſtabliſhed in the preſent truth: Truth being, as God ſpake of his commandement, not in heaven, that thou ſhouldſt ſay, Who ſhall goe up for us to heaven, and bring it us, and cauſe us to heare it? Neither is it beyond the ſea, that thou ſhouldſt ſay, Who ſhall goe over the ſea for us, and bring it us, and cauſe us to heare it, that we may doe it? No, but the truth is very neere us: As <hi>Salomon</hi> of the Turtle, ſo of truth; The voice of truth is heard in our land. Set that truth as a ſeale upon your heart, and as a ſignet upon your arme, binde it for a ſigne upon your hand, and let it bee as frontlets betweene your eies; be as tender over truth as the apple of your eie; ſooner let the Sunne wander from his courſe, than ye from truth. In our
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:17662:25"/> Letany we pray the Magiſtrates may have grace given them to maintaine truth. It was Chriſts praier for his, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 17. Sanctifie them with thy truth: and the God of truth confirme and keepe you in his ſo excellent truth; Truths excellency. So have you the firſt part.</p>
            <p>And can it then be, a thing ſo highly ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent as truth, ſhould finde ſo harſh en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertainment as enmitie? Can ſo bright beames beget ſo blacke cloudes? Yes, as <hi>Salomon</hi> tels of the price to get wiſedome in the hand of a foole that hath no heart to it; for all that true price of Truth, come we now to view how fooles miſpriſe it, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertayning it with enmitie, <hi>Enemy for tel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling truth,</hi> That's now the ſecond part. <hi>Ergo inimicus;</hi> an <hi>Ergo</hi> ſo incongruous, ſo inconſequent, as may well drive the hearer with <hi>Auſtin</hi> into admiration and amaze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, why men indued with underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, ſhould be ſo ſollicitouſly ſtudious a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout courſes of ſtars, flowings of ſea, and more frothy things, and yet the whilſt ſo retchleſſe of Truth, neerlier concerning them; and make him likewiſe paſsionate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:17662:26"/> expoſtulate as <hi>Auſtin,</hi> Shall other vaine men vaunt themſelves happie in imbrace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of other beauties, and Chriſtians ſlight the imbracing of beautifull Truth? Shall they boaſt a happineſſe in ſitting downe to eate and drinke, and we not ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend a bleſſedneſſe, in being fed and feaſted with truth? Shall they <hi>coenare fabu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis,</hi> and wee not <hi>veritate?</hi> Shall they crake of beds of roſes and ſweet odours, and Chriſtians take no pleaſure in the fragrant inſpiration of truth? Shall they tripudiate in muſique, and Chriſtians not triumph in the melody of truth? Shall they delight in the light of the Sunne, and wee not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light in the light of Truth? Shall ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny love lightneſſe, and any ſet ſo light by lovely truth, as thus to entertaine it with enmity? <hi>Ergo inimicus;</hi> A ſtrange <hi>Ergo,</hi> yet not more ſtrange than true, truth being ſo frequently haunted with hatred, as <hi>Calvin</hi> wrote to the Chriſtian King, <hi>Evangelij ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius,</hi> as oppoſition, the bad genius, as it were waiting upon the Goſpell; ſo enmity a familiar as it were, every where dogging truth. The ſaying, <hi>Veritas odium parit,</hi> not
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:17662:26"/> more familiar than the thing, though not a generall truth as in the Poet; and yet <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctantius</hi> thinkes he ſpake it, <hi>qua ſi divino ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritu inſtinctus;</hi> not ſo true of all, ſaies <hi>Ierome,</hi> yet too too true of too too many. Whilſt as the beautifull Nymphes are ſaid to have brought forth the ill favoured Fawnes and Satyrs; ſo truth bringing forth hatred, or rather enmity; like the Dragon in the <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velation,</hi> ſtanding before the woman tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velling, ready to devour what ſhee ſhould bring forth. As in <hi>Geneſis, The Lord ſaid,</hi> is by &amp; by encountred with <hi>The Serpent ſaid,</hi> ſo is telling truth encountred thus with enmity. When <hi>Eliah</hi> told <hi>Ahab</hi> truth, <hi>Haſt thou found mee, O mine enemy?</hi> ſaid hee; the like was <hi>Micaiah's</hi> caſe with <hi>Ahab,</hi> the man of Gods caſe with <hi>Ieroboam, Iohn Baptiſts</hi> with <hi>Herod,</hi> St. <hi>Stevens</hi> with the Iewes; ſo perſecuted they the Prophets, thus enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taind they truth with enmitie: And as <hi>Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſtes</hi> ſpake, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, That which hath been, is that which ſhall bee; it hath beene ſo, and 'twill be ſo, be it ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſo unreaſonable that it ſhould bee ſo: there is demonſtrative reaſon upon reaſon,
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:17662:27"/> why it will bee ſo: There being three things (ſaies <hi>Aristotle</hi>) <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, three things that breed enmity, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>ira, incommodatio, criminatio,</hi> diſpleaſure, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>profit, diſcredit; why in all theſe, truth be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing not for moſt mens turne, corrupt na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture makes them thus turne enemies to the tellers of truth. Firſt, <hi>Ira:</hi> as they write of ſome creatures to have the gall in the eare, <hi>fel in aure,</hi> the hearing of truth galls them; as <hi>Peter</hi> told <hi>Simon Magus,</hi> Thou art in the gall of bitterneſſe: telling of truth puts them into the gall of bitterneſſe, angers them, nettles them. And as ulcerous men uſe to ſhrinke at the lighteſt touch, yea ſometimes ſhreeke even at the very ſuſpici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, the imagination of touching; truth told touching, or ſeeming but to touch their ſores, makes them take on like waſpes, like the mad man, prickt to cure his ſore, they flye upon the Chirurgion: <hi>Tange montes &amp; fumigabunt;</hi> the leaſt touch of truth makes them fume and fret like the vapours of the thunder-bolt, which ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver linne working till they have vented themſelves with terror; they never leave
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:17662:27"/> brauling till they have exhaled their an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, vented their enmitie: Becauſe truth telling wil not let them wallow ſo ſecure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly as otherwiſe they would, not ſuffer them to curd and ſettle on their lees, as the Prophet <hi>Zephany</hi> ſpeakes, as they would: a <hi>quare impedit</hi> therfore ſo quarrels the truth, as that the tellers thereof are driven often to that <hi>Dilemma</hi> of <hi>Agathon,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, &amp;c. If I pleaſe thee, I ſhal not tell the truth; and if I tell the truth, I ſhall not pleaſe thee, but procure enmitie. Secondly, <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commodatio,</hi> truth telling is againſt their profit, preiudicial to their gainfull practice of lying and falſhood: therefore ſay they of the truth teller, as they in the ſecond of <hi>Wiſedome</hi> ſpake of the righteous, He is not for our profit, he is contrary to our doing, therfore rebuke him; Dunghill men, like <hi>Aeſops</hi> Cocke, ſetting more by the Barley corne of profite, than the pearle of truth; of the ſwiniſh race, Gergeſens, willing ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to lack Chriſt, than loſe the leaſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moditie. Thirdly, <hi>Criminatio,</hi> truth telling accuſes them, endites them, arraigns them, condemnes them, brands them and their
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:17662:28"/> courſes. As <hi>David</hi> couples Light &amp; Truth together, Truth, like Light, being of a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covering nature, making things manifeſt. <hi>Therefore</hi> (as S. <hi>Iohn</hi> ſpake) <hi>men love darke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe more than light, becauſe their deedes are evill;</hi> a darke ſhop being beſt for badde wares: therefore as theeves ſeeke to put out the candle, they would have the light Truth put out. A Scorner (as <hi>Salomon</hi> ſayes) loving not one that reproveth him; Truth reproving them, therfore reprove they the Truth. Tell one of your Politicians <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinian's</hi> truth, That that's the beſt reaſon which makes moſt for Religion, that the beſt policy which makes moſt for Pietie; why, this truth croſsing his proiects and purpoſes, the teller may take his bill, and ſit downe quickly, and write Enmitie. Tell a covetous man St. <hi>Pauls</hi> truth, That the love of monie is the roote of all evill, yee offer him loſſe, ye touch his free-hold, yee are a treſpaſſer to his trade, an enemy. Tell the luxurious man that <hi>theorem</hi> of Truth, That temperance is the razor of ſuperfluities, and the rule of neceſſaries; and that this whole life ought to be a kind
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:17662:28"/> of Lent; Away with your thred-bare Schollers poſies; ye bring us into the wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſſe to ſtarve us, ye are an enemy. I will not procure more enemies by more inſtances; ſuffice it, <hi>Nec in caeteris contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rium eſt videre:</hi> That if as <hi>Gideon</hi> once made proclamation in the audience of the people, Who ſo is timorous or faint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hearted, let him depart, ſo every one whoſe heart riſeth againſt truth told, ſhould depart, we ſhould ſoon have more roome, auditories would ſoone bee thin, <hi>Vel duo, vel nemo.</hi> Light is good, but yet to bad eies, offenſive. Honie is ſweet, but yet to wounds, ſmarting; truth is wholeſome, but yet to moſt, diſtaſtfull: like that bloudy water, ſweete and pota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to Hebrewes, ſaies <hi>Ioſephus,</hi> but ſowre and would not downe with Egyptians. Then bee that ſchoole diſtinction true, that truth in the univerſall, <hi>ſub ratione ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ri,</hi> cannot be hated, yet in the particular, <hi>ſub ratione contrarij,</hi> ſo is it uſually thus ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted; though no man can hate truth <hi>in uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſali,</hi> while it onely pleades it ſelfe, yet <hi>in particulari,</hi> when it comes thus to preſſe
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:17662:29"/> upon themſelves: As the Friar wittily told the people that the truth he preach'd, was like holy water, which every one call a pace for, yet when it came to be caſt on them, they would turne aſide their face: even they that will call faſt for Truth, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not yet away to have it caſt in their face; even they that could like truth if it would onely ſhew it ſelfe, miſlike it, when it comes thus to ſhew them themſelves; they that love truth <hi>lucentem,</hi> hate it thus <hi>redarguentem,</hi> ſaies <hi>Auſtin;</hi> and ſo ſaies <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broſe,</hi> becauſe no man would be reproved for erring; therefore becomes hee enemy thus to truth reprehending. <hi>Veritas ideo ſemper inviſa eſt, eo quod is qui peccat, vult habere liberum peccandi locum,</hi> ſaies <hi>Lactan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius,</hi> Becauſe every offender would have his full ſwindge without controule, ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore take they offence at truth: as hee that delicately compoſes himſelfe to ſleepe, prohibites all lowder noiſe, and procures ſome gentle murmure; ſo loving to bee lulled in their ſecurity, ſome ſweete <hi>Syren</hi> ſounds they can away with, but this ſame ſhrill trumpet of Truth, away with that.
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:17662:29"/> So diſtempered, ſo ill dieted, ſo unadviſed moſt men are, as readily to ſwallow flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teries, digeſt fables, concoct errors, and yet truth with them to be ſo hard of dige<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion, as thus to ſtomacke that, thus turne that into bitterneſſe, <hi>Enmity.</hi> That where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as we uſually ſay, Bitter as gall, we might ſtronglier expreſſe it (ſaid <hi>Vega</hi> well) by ſaying, Bitter as Truth. That as the Turke taunted ſome Chriſtians at Conſtantino<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, who ſaid that they came thither to ſuffer for the Truth, That they needed not have come ſo farre for that, ſeeing had they but told the Truth at home, they ſhould not have miſſed ſuffering for it: telling truth needes not travell farre for enmity; enmity will encounter it at home, whereſoever. That as for all Chriſt bid woe to the man by whom the offence commeth, offences yet will come, ſo it ſhall ſurely be woe upon woe to him, by whom enmity comes upon truth, enmity will yet come upon it; though this laurell of Truth will be bitter to them that bite it, bite at it yet men will; though as <hi>Igna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius</hi> ſpeakes, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, &amp;c. to
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:17662:30"/> follow any that falls from Truth, be for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feiture of the Kingdome of heaven; yet will men follow the foes of Truth, ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy againſt it, be enemies to telling Truth; that as they uſe to ſay, Plaine dealing is a iewell, but hee that uſes it dies a beggar: bee Truth never ſuch a iewell, the teller may probably account aforehand, this way to be a loſer by it; let him never feed himſelfe with vaine expectation, that the trade of truth telling is a plauſible, inſinu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ating, welcome, winning profeſsion: <hi>An expectas ut Quintilianus ametur?</hi> Let him rather count himſelfe to be borne, as <hi>Iere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie,</hi> a contentious man, a man that ſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth with the whole earth: as <hi>Luther</hi> ſaid of preaching, <hi>Praedicare nihil aliud eſt, quàm derivare in ſe furorem, &amp;c.</hi> That to preach (preach home as hee uſed) was nothing elſe but to ſtirre up the fury of Hell, Satan, World againſt a man; ſo telling of truth to be a ſtirrer of rage, a ſigne which will be ſpoken againſt. Let never the truth tel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler dreame of comfits and ſweet meates; reckon he thus to eate his Paſſeover with ſowre herbes, thus to bee fed with bitter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:17662:30"/> and filled as with wormwood, to have this wilde gourd Enmity ſhred into his pot. Never ſay, I had not thought it; S. <hi>Peter</hi> hath fore-told it, <hi>The way of Truth ſhall bee evill ſpoken of;</hi> and S. <hi>Paul</hi> here found it, enmity for telling Truth,
<q>Am I therefore become your enemy? &amp;c.</q> So have you the firſt and ſecond part.</p>
            <p>And this apprehenſion, this account a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forehand, as Darts fore-ſeen dint-leſſe, and fore-warned fore-armed; may paſſe as a preparative to the following point, The enduring of that enmitie for telling truth: that's now the third and laſt part. The Apoſtle here, while hee thus increpates their enmitie for his telling them truth, intimates his owne reſolution, ſo endu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring that enmitie in behalfe of Truth. <hi>Non timuit vituperari, vel odio haberi, &amp;c.</hi> ſaid <hi>Anſelme</hi> upon it; Hee feared no mans ill will to him, ſo hee might manifeſt his good will to Truth: And ſo 'tis alſo <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roms</hi> inference hereupon, out of the 40. of <hi>Eſay, Lift up thy voyce with ſtrength, lift it up and be not affraid:</hi> for, as <hi>Eſay</hi> ſpake againe, <hi>Who art thou, that thou ſhouldeſt feare a mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:17662:31"/> man, and the ſonne of man, which ſhall bee made as graſſe, and forgetteſt the Lord thy ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker?</hi> ſo what art thou, that thou ſhouldeſt feare this enmitie, and forget the truth? for though they ſhrewdly ſay, <hi>Qui vult dimitti à Domino, dicat illi veritatem,</hi> He that would be put from his Maſter, let him tell him truth; yet is it to be ſaid, Hee that would have God his good Maſter, muſt tell the truth. As he well compares Truth to <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bekah</hi> with her two twins: Brings truth telling thus forth the hate of men? it brings forth withall the other twin, the love of God too; that be it with the world, as they ſay, a cold occupation to tell the truth, a bleſſed occupation is it yet with God: how-ever fleſh and bloud ſay, Maſter, pit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie thy ſelfe, this enmitie ſhall not be unto thee; and whatſoever witches children whiſper to the contrarie. For, come on (ſayes the Temporiſt to the Truth-teller) you are ſo keene of this truth-tell, you'l marre all: wote you not what Pope <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genius</hi> ſaid, <hi>Hoc verum eſſe ſi ipſe velit &amp; non aliter,</hi> That this or that was true if his Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe, his Greatneſſe would have it ſo,
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:17662:31"/> and not otherwiſe? as if great Ones gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Warrants of Truth, as of the Peace? Remember ye not, your owne book ſayes, Time to be trueſt, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, as in <hi>Xenophon;</hi> and Truth to be Times daughter, as in the Poet? And why will any of you then, ſet the daughter at variance with the mother, and not rather handle the matter ſo, as the daughter Truth may ever be conſonant to the mother Time? yea, &amp; conformable ſo with place too, every place being not for telling every truth? for bee Truth (as they ſay) a Sergeant, yet places there bee exempted from that arreſt, as well as o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. <hi>Affirmatio veritatis obligat ſemper, ſed non ad ſemper, ſed pro loco &amp; tempore,</hi> Truth telling hath it times and places, and <hi>Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>centia</hi> a citie as well as <hi>Verona: Loquimini placentia,</hi> or if ye cannot fall to that faw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning veine, as M. <hi>Bradford</hi> ſaid of Maſsing and Preaching, that the Maſſe bites not men, nor makes them bluſh as preaching does; cannot ye meddle onely with tooth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe truths, as <hi>Balak</hi> bid, Neither curſe nor bleſſe at all? ſerve in as in <hi>Iob,</hi> only the white of an egge without any taſte at all?
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:17662:32"/> Or if needes you muſt be tampring with Truth, cannot yee candy it over with a ſcepticall neutrality, or over-caſt it with ſome cloudy obſcurity, <hi>Verbis coopertis,</hi> as ſlily the Romaniſt; either as the Pope plaies with two points about Chriſt and <hi>Marie,</hi> onely problematically not poſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tively, betweene two to ſhift at pleaſure; or as <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> ſet forth his Acroamatickes, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>? How-ever you meete with them that tell you, that the Prophets and Apoſtles, &amp; Chriſt himſelfe propounded Truth naked, yet 'tis none of the worſt obſervations you ſhall meet with in <hi>Oleaſter,</hi> The holy Prophets, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially to great Ones, to have ſpoken moſt an end in Parables; and Ieſus himſelfe fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently to have ſpoken in Parables: that ſince people are ſo ſhie of the naked Truth, Truth might ſo bee preſented in ſome diſguiſe unto them. Take but the triviall inſtance; be Truth as good diet as a Partridge, yet is it not to bee ſerv'd in raw, or feathers and all; but cook'd and ſeaſon'd, <hi>Sale prudentiae temperata;</hi> at leaſt bee ſo wiſe as to tarry till downe-right
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:17662:32"/> Truth bee demanded of you, and ſo drawne from you. No, hence Satan; often is it ſaid, <hi>Then Ieſus anſwered and ſaid,</hi> when yet none asked him, he anſwering then to the Truth ſpeaking in his conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence. And as <hi>Fulgentius</hi> truely ſpake to king <hi>Traſimund,</hi> The ſilence that affirmeth not truth, confirmeth errour, and little to chuſe between nilling to declare truth, &amp; willing to deny it. And as <hi>Tertullian</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellently, <hi>Nihil Veritas erubeſcit niſi ſolum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modò abſcondi,</hi> Truth bluſheth at nothing more than to bee hidden; Truth ſeeking no corners, nor ever yet could temporize; nor more than the Moone ſtaies her courſe in heaven, for the barking of dogs at it here on earth, forbeares for any ſuch Enmity. But (as ſaies <hi>Auſtin</hi>) Though men bely the Moone in her defects, and revile the Starres, nicknaming them, <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne, Iupiter, Mercury,</hi> and worſe, <hi>Venus,</hi> the Starres yet continue their courſes; No crimination of hereſie, no calumniation of ſchiſme, no imputation of noveltie daunts the Truth, no nor diſheartens the <hi>Pauls,</hi> the true Truth-tellers neither; no
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:17662:33"/> virulent breath can ſtaine ſuch Starres; but though the adverſary write a booke a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them, yet will they binde it as a Crowne unto them, as in <hi>Iob:</hi> though they revile them as they doe, the ſchoole of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan, the heard of Antichriſt, the reprobate congregation, looſe Apoſtates, turkiſh Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guenots, worſe than Infidels, prophane Hell-hounds, falſe Goſpellers, yea Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiques, from whoſe mouths even Truth it ſelfe proceeding, is not to bee entertai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, ſaid their Friar: yet ſhaking off thoſe virulences, as <hi>Paul</hi> did the Viper, <hi>After the way which they call Hereſie,</hi> will they tell the Truth; remembring that terrible ſpeech of <hi>Auſtins, Quicunque metu, &amp;c.</hi> that whoſoever for feare of any power hides Truth, provokes Gods wrath a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt himſelfe, as one that feareth man more than God. It was <hi>Ieremies</hi> complaint in his time, that people then bent their tongues like bowes for lies; but had no courage for the truth upon the earth, not valiant for the truth upon the earth, as now we reade it: nor want their iuſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaints in that key; The world-through,
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:17662:33"/> 
               <hi>diminutae ſunt veritates à filijs hominam,</hi> complained <hi>David.</hi> And the tale goes of Truth lying ſicke, and like to die without confeſsion, becauſe no man could bee found that would be her Confeſſour; too too many indeede every where ſlighting Truth, ſetting at nought ſo great ſalvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Yet not after the wont of way-ward men, ſo to bemoane what wee want, as not to bleſſe God for what wee have; chuſe I rather hence to cheare up Truth, with the courage of her tellers now, and cannot but ſay, much like as Chriſt of the woman that powred the ointment on his head: Verily, whereſoever Truth ſhall be preached, the truth of many of this meri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dian to the Truth, is worthy to bee told for a memoriall of them; <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, as S. <hi>Iohn</hi> ſpeakes, how they have beene fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low-helpers to the Truth; as in <hi>Athenago<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ras</hi> both <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>de veritate,</hi> by ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the truth unto the religious, and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>pro veritate,</hi> for the truth againſt the erroneous. And good luck have they with their glory, and ride on proſperouſly becauſe of Truth, and let it never bee ſaid
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:17662:34"/> that the adverſaries (thoſe pioners, whoſe occupation is onely to undermine the truth) like theſe Galatians here, bewitch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed them that they ſhould not obey the Truth. Shall any of them bee ſtouter for fraudulent equivocations, lying miracles, falſe doctrines, than we for Gods Truth? as <hi>Tertullian</hi> ſpake of Heretiques then, <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtatas poſtatas noſtros gloriâ obligant, quia veritate non poſſunt?</hi> Shall they prevaile more over ours with trickes, than we over theirs with Truth? It hath beene ſaid that our word True, comes <hi>ab Hetruſco,</hi> and <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truria</hi> fondly hath been termed <hi>regio veri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatis:</hi> And O that this region might not onely ſo be ſaid, but ever be the region of Truth; and as it was the firſt kingdome that univerſally embraced the truth of the Goſpell, ſo to the laſt it may continue conſtant for the Truth. Never was there in the world title of more honour, than when God in the 8. of <hi>Zachary,</hi> ſaid, <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem ſhall bee called a city of truth;</hi> No nor of more profit neither: for when <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roz</hi> ſhall be curſed, the inhabitants there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of bitterly curſed, becauſe they came not
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:17662:34"/> to helpe the Lord; bleſſed ſhall yee, all yee be that come to the help of Truth againſt the malignant: for doe not yee miſdeeme your ſelves, as though there were no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther place for this telling truth but the Pulpit, no other helpers of truth beſides the Preachers, no other partakers of truth beſides Prophets and Prophets ſonnes. As God ſaid of Corinth, <hi>I have much people in this citie:</hi> Truth hath much people, many friends in City, Court, Country; yea even out of the mouth of babes and ſucklings hath it ſtrength to ſilence the enemy. Then what though you or you cannot do much for Truth? doe your beſt for it; and if there be a willing minde, it is accepted accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to that a man hath, and not accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to that hee hath not, as <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth. And O how learned <hi>Fulgentius</hi> prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes yongue <hi>Donatus,</hi> that being ſet upon by the Arrians, though hee had not the skil to defend the Truth with his tongue, had yet a will to maintaine the Truth in his heart; though he could not unlooſe all their cunning trickes, he could yet hold faſt the concluſion, Truth: and hee that
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:17662:35"/> (for hee could neither write nor reade) could not Clerkly ſubſcribe his name to Truths confeſsion, could yet manly draw bloud of himſelfe, wherewith to ſet his ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>k<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> do it; And ſhee that for want of learning could not diſpute Chriſts cauſe, could yee bee content to die for it; and Were every haire of my head a man, I would burne them all, ſaid a third, rather than go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> from Truth. Nor conceive I any, either more powerfull oppoſition againſt the enemy to withſtand him, or proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble perſwaſion with the adverſary to win him, than ſuch undaunted reſolution for the Truth. When <hi>Iuſtin Martyr,</hi> then a Platoniſt, heard the Chriſtians ill ſpoken of, and yet ſaw them ſo conſtantly bent to endure any hardſhip for the truth of their cauſe, hee concluded with himſelfe, that ſure they could be no vicious volup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous men. And who knoweth whether the conſtant keenneſſe of the profeſſors of Truth, may gaine a good report to the Truth, even of them which yet are with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the Truth? or if not, as he that was to be burned with the booke of the <hi>Revela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi>
               <pb n="63" facs="tcp:17662:35"/> by him, held himſelfe happy to ſuffer martyrdome with ſuch a marrow: hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe will it be thus to ſuffer enmity for ſuch a friend as Truth: Truth which is to be preferr'd even before friendſhip, as the very Heathen man could ſay, being never to be preiudiced by any ſuch Enmity, but to continue Truths friends, who ever therefore become our enemies.</p>
            <q>Am I therefore become your enemy? &amp;c.</q>
            <p>Now the God of Truth, &amp;c.</p>
            <closer>Laus Deo.</closer>
         </div>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:17662:36"/>
            <pb n="65" facs="tcp:17662:36"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Acts 19. verſ. 28. the latter part.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>And cryed out, ſaying, Great is Diana of the Epheſians.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Ecurus licet Aeneam Rutulúmque,</hi> as he ſaid; A man may ſafely ſpeake of <hi>Aeneas</hi> and <hi>Rutulus: Nulli gravis est percuſſus Achil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les;</hi> To heare of wounded <hi>Achilles</hi> galls no man now: and a tale of Troy troubles no man here. The Prieſt of Bethel, though he could not abide that <hi>Amos</hi> in his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecie ſhould grate upon the houſe of Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael, yet if hee would flye away into the land of Iudah, and prophecie there, he was not againſt it. Though the Iewes could not endure, that <hi>Ieremy</hi> ſhould meddle with the burden of Iudah and Ieruſalem, yet if hee would prophecie againſt Edom, and Moab, and Ammon, and them a farre off, hee might for all them; they felt no
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:17662:37"/> ſmart, no hurt done. According to which reckoning, this Text here, may now at manie hands probably promiſe it ſelfe a freer paſſage, a friendlier welcome; as medling not, you ſee, with matters pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent now, or neerer home, but paſt and far off, matters of another Meridian, not only ſtrictly Geometrically, but very ſenſibly a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loofe from us, as farre as Aſia; nighing not Europaeans, but Epheſians; not mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning any our defects, but only their <hi>Diana,</hi> how they cryed out, ſaying,
<q>Great is Diana of the Epheſians.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Howbeit, amidſt ſuch diverſitie, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed daintineſſe of hearers, leſt that relliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo with ſome prove ſo diſtaſtefull to others, that, as dealt the Tribes with <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hoboam, What portion have we in David? wee have no inheritance, no part in him;</hi> and ſo they departed: ſo any now ſay, Wee have no portion, no ſhare in that in hand; it pertayning ſo peculiarly to Epheſians, we have no part in it, and ſo they depart. As <hi>Ionathan</hi> concluded with <hi>David,</hi> That if he cry'd to the boy, Behold, the arrowes are beyond thee; he was then to be gone:
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:17662:37"/> the cry here being about <hi>Diana</hi> and Ephe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſians, Behold, the arrowes here are all beyond us, let us away; Know they alſo, that as <hi>Nathan,</hi> though hee begun with a tale of two men and a ſheepe, yet brought it about in the end to, <hi>Thou art the man;</hi> This Text here, though about forreiners, may happely be brought to touch even upon Domeſticks too: and though, as in Arraſſe foulded up, little yet appeare to purpoſe, unfoulded it may reveale that, <hi>quod ad te pertinet obe;</hi> not onely as <hi>Daniel</hi> ſaid, <hi>My Lord, the dreame be to them that hate thee, and the interpretation thereof to thine e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies:</hi> the Diſcourſe and Doctrine here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of may attach, not onely them that hate us, and the interpretation thereof light all up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on our enemies, but partly reflect even up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on our ſelves too: And as the Sunne, though it riſe in the Eaſt, ſets yet in the Weſt (and ſome have ſhrewdly gheſſed as much of Religion too); by that time the Text hath gone it circuit, it may come to ſet farre from where it roſe; Epheſus come neerer England, and <hi>Diana</hi> be brought home to our owne doores, and
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:17662:38"/> we alſo in our Dialect, bee many heard crying out, ſaying,
<q>Great is Diana of the Epheſians.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Which words, albeit in this their owne ſituation, not unlike ſome maze, which though ſpreading but to little quantity of ground, would yet require an houres treading; yet to make roome for direct and diſtinct proceeding, wee may dilate the words, either into the manner and the matter. The manner, <hi>Crying out;</hi> The matter, <hi>Great Diana;</hi> or in as much as the matter here of their Cry is fabulous, into their prologue, and their fable. The prologue, <hi>They cry'd out:</hi> The fable, <hi>Great is Diana.</hi> Or who ſo liſt entitle their enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſe here, the birth of the mountaines, here's the travell, <hi>They cry'd out;</hi> and the birth delivered, <hi>Great Diana:</hi> Plainly, as the voice bid <hi>Eſay</hi> cry, and he ſaid, <hi>What ſhall I cry?</hi> here's the cry, and that which is cry'd, <hi>Great Diana.</hi> Then lend me but your ſilence, whilſt I ſpeake of their Cry, and your attention, whilſt I declare their <hi>Diana.</hi> As <hi>Salomon</hi> ſaid, that from the ſight and conſideration even of the field of the
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:17662:38"/> ſlothfull, and the vineyard of the man voide of underſtanding, hee received in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction, <hi>Inſtruunt non ſolùm docentes, ſed &amp; errantes:</hi> from the conſideration of the carriage, even of theſe ſuperſtitious Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trous men, there will (God willing) in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction be derived, and their crying out then, call upon us now, and their <hi>Diana</hi> there, diſcover others devices elſe-where, concentrique with theſe of the Epheſians, crying out, ſaying,
<q>Great is Diana of the Epheſians.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>They cryed out.</hi> As <hi>David</hi> queſtioned the ſea, What ailed thee, that thou fleddeſt? and his ſoule, Why, art thou ſo diſquieted? Why, what ail'd them, what diſquieted them, thus to cry out? Why, this was the matter, <hi>Demetrius</hi> and his fellow craftſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, Silver-ſmiths by occupation, made certaine ſiluer Temples, as our former Tranſlation; ſilver ſhrines, as this now calls them. <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> thinkes they were a kinde of little coffers, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>Carthuſian</hi> a kinde of gay little houſes, with <hi>Diana's</hi> image encloſed in them. Other, Images repreſenting &amp; made like unto her Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, either to be offered in that Temple
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:17662:39"/> there, <hi>Votiva Templa,</hi> as they call them; or to be borne about with them whitherſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever they went, as wont that Philoſopher in <hi>Ammianus; Thecas ſtatuarum,</hi> certaine caſes with her image in them, ſo ſundry expound them. <hi>Beza</hi> criticking the word, thinkes they were peeces of coine, ſuch as he ſaies himſelfe hath ſeene, with the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſians <hi>Diana's</hi> image, and a repreſenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of her Temple ſtamped on them. Temples, or Shrines, or Coffers, or Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, or Caſes, or Coines, call them what you will, certaine Gewgawes they were, ſuch as I would have reſembled, to the Philiſtines coffer with the golden images of their Mice and Emerods in it, but that the Ieſuite himſelfe full properly reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles them to ſome images of their owne; and withall records the praiſes of Biſhop <hi>Eligius</hi> for his ſingular skill, in making ſuch ſilver caſes for Saints, which in any caſe are to be deckt up with gold and ſil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, and every precious thing, ſaies he; Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh puppets, a kinne to theſe Epheſian bables, with <hi>Diana's</hi> picture in them, which they made and ſold to ſuch fond folkes, ſuch ſilly people, ſtrangers, or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:17662:39"/> that would buy them. Now holy <hi>Paul</hi> by his powerfull preaching there, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lienating the minds of many people from thoſe gods, no gods, made with hands; the fellowes fore-ſeeing, that as their gaine (of which wee ſhall after ſpeake) ſo their goddeſſe (on which alone, their tongues run here in the Text) their goddeſſe was in danger to be diſcountenanced by it, her temple to bee deſpiſed, and her magnifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence to bee deſtroied, as that their reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>new, ſo this their religion likely thereby to bee impaired and endammaged, aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled and angry thereat, they cryed out, <hi>Great is Diana.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As divine ſtory tells of the Idoll <hi>Dagon,</hi> falling downe before the Arke of the Lord; and Eccleſiaſticall ſtory, how at Chriſts comming into Egypt, all the Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges there fell downe: ſo at the preaching of this Goſpell then, Idolatry beginning to ſhake and ſtagger, as <hi>Epiphanius</hi> tells of <hi>Eliſaeus,</hi> how at his birth in Gilgall, the golden Calfe in Selom, bellowing out ſo lowd, as that the noiſe was heard at Ieru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem, the <hi>prieſt</hi> interpreted it, that a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet was that day borne, who ſhould
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:17662:40"/> breake in peeces their carved and moulten Images: ſo <hi>Pauls</hi> preaching battring thus, and crying downe the Idolls, they held it high time to take on, and bellow, and cry out thus for their <hi>Diana.</hi> So as out of this crying of theirs here, for the upholding of their <hi>Diana,</hi> as was ſaid of old of her ſelfe, that ſhe had three viſages, <hi>tria virginis ora Dianae,</hi> ſo (mee thinkes) I ſee three heads hence appeare unto us. Firſt, their Tender<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe in apprehending ſo their <hi>Diana's</hi> danger and diſgrace; they ſoone ſaw, yea fore-ſaw, and fore-caſt it afore-hand. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, their Earneſtneſſe in appearing for her; no ſooner heard they of her danger, but forthwith in her defence, they cry'd out. And thirdly, their Iointneſſe in under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taking on her behalfe, in the whole heape of them, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, that's the word in the whole croud and convocation of them. I do not finde one mute among them here, but all conſonants, all crying out. Tender<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe in apprehending, Earneſtneſſe in ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearing, Iointneſſe in undertaking; three diſpoſitions of theſe Heathen, in regard of their goddeſſe and idolatry: which when wee ſhall have weighed comparatively
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:17662:40"/> with their defects, in many of us Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, reſpectively to our God and Religion, this their tenderneſſe, that way upbraiding our inſenſibleneſſe, their earneſtneſſe our remiſſeneſſe, their iointneſſe our diſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions. As <hi>Demoſthenes</hi> wont to grieve if handy craftſmen were earlier up at worke than he; and <hi>Pambo</hi> wept to ſee the naugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty woman more buſie and ſollicitous to pleaſe lewd men, than hee himſelfe was ſtudious and diligent to pleaſe God; if we have not foreheads of flint, and hearts as the neather milſtone, it may make us both bluſh and grieve to ſee theſe Mechanickes here, more paſsionately and heartily affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted toward their baggage <hi>Diana,</hi> than many of us are to the bleſſed Deity; wee, being now ſo backward and cold for Gods true worſhip, and they all here ſo forward and keene for her idolatrous worſhip, as thus to cry out for it, ſaying,
<q>Great is Diana of the Epheſians.</q>
            </p>
            <p>For the firſt then, their Tenderneſſe here over their Idoll. How-ever <hi>Lorinus</hi> liſt ſay, <hi>Non minùs affabrè, &amp;c.</hi> that <hi>Deme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trius</hi> here compos'd his oration to them, as artificially as ever hee made ſhrine for
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:17662:41"/> her; for ought I deſcry in it, with a little Rhetorique, leſſe than many lay-Preacher puts into every period to the people; he wrought ſo quickly and deepely upon them, that no ſooner underſtood they by his ſpeech, of any hazzard of harme to <hi>Diana,</hi> but with a quick eare to the touch of that ſtring, out of a feeling apprehenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, a tender reſentment of it, they cry'd out. That though the harme (if yee marke the context) the harme here to <hi>Diana's</hi> goodly maieſty, was yet farre of, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, ſay the words before, <hi>Futurum,</hi> it was yet to come to paſſe, <hi>deſtrui incipiet,</hi> as ſome ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der it; her deſtruction was yet to beginne, her harme, at the moſt, was but a ham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mering, her danger yet but a breeding <hi>in Embryone,</hi> as it were, and ſo might miſcar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry by ſome aborſment, or otherwiſe ebbe into emptineſſe: yet ſee here, as <hi>Zebul</hi> ſaid to <hi>Gaal,</hi> Thou ſeeſt the ſhadow of the mountaines as if they were men, thou art affraid of a ſhadow; the very ſhadow of danger to their goddeſſe, they were very ſhie and ſenſible of, <hi>Atque omnes metuentes expendere caſus.</hi> And as <hi>Eliah</hi> out of a little cloud ariſing, diſcern'd a great raine a
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:17662:41"/> comming; whilſt her danger was ſcarce yet in the clouds, in the vapours, but ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, they ſpied the ſtorme a comming. As when <hi>Hanniball</hi> beſieg'd Saguntum, a confederate citie with Rome, <hi>Sylius</hi> ſaies, he then beat upon the Capitoll at Rome, <hi>Et extremis pulſat Capitolia terris;</hi> every re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buke that <hi>Pauls</hi> preaching gave to any I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doll, they thought it rapt at their <hi>Diana's</hi> doore: and ſo not lingring till <hi>Hanniball</hi> came to the gates indeed, not delaying till the dart came ſo neere, that it could not bee declin'd, not neglecting what they thought belong'd unto their peace, till as <hi>Demades</hi> ſaid of the Athenians, they were driven to mourning gownes, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, as <hi>Homer</hi> loved to ſay: Wary were they before the wound. As the Bore being queſtioned why hee ſtood whetting his teeth ſo, whilſt yet none aſſailed him, wiſely anſwered, That it would be then too late to whet them when hee was to uſe them; and therefore whetted them ſo before danger, that hee might have them ready in danger. As <hi>Demoſthenes</hi> adviſed the Athenians, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, that they would not expect till evill came,
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:17662:42"/> but prevent it; and to deale with their dangers, as men doe with ſerpents and vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers, of which though happely they never have beene ſtung or bitten, yet ſeeing any of them, they tarry not till it ſting or bite, but before harme done, forth-with ſeek to kill it, to cruſh the Scorpion at the firſt ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance: So theſe here, wiſe in their ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration, counting providence better than repentance, not waiting and gaping after event, the Schoole-maſter of fooles, as <hi>Fabius</hi> call'd it, not onely <hi>ante bellum auxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lium,</hi> but even <hi>ante tubam tremor,</hi> affected with what was not yet effected, appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſive aforehand of her danger, they <hi>cryed out:</hi> ſo tender were they over their <hi>Diana.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now from them look we homeward, and make the proſpect upon our ſelves, in parallel with this Heatheniſh; feel wee now this Chriſtian pulſe, how it beats in aequiparant occurrences: Are we all thus tender over the glory of our God? are wee all thus iealous for the Lord of Hoſts? are wee all thus apprehenſive, thus feelingly forecaſting againſt all ſuch paſſages, as may at any time ſeeme to threaten any de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triment
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:17662:42"/> to Gods cauſe, Religion? <hi>Vtinam, molliſsimum adverbium,</hi> call'd <hi>Scaliger</hi> it, Too ſoft an adverb for a Philoſopher: yet ſoft as it is, <hi>Vtinam,</hi> I would Chriſtians all had, and had had ſuch ſoftneſſe on this ſide, ſuch tenderneſſe over religion; then had not that truculent enemy of Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie growne to that greatneſſe through their dulneſſe; <hi>ignavia noſtra magni,</hi> as hee avoucheth it, as having beene and ſtill be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing many ſo farre from ſuch tenderneſſe; that have not wee rather that way, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, as the Spirit of God uſes to call it, a kind of hoof as it were over many of our hearts? <hi>Callum obductum, corneas fibras,</hi> brawny breaſts, horny heart-ſtrings? hard and unſenſible? <hi>Pectus quoque robora fiunt.</hi> As Ducklings ſtoop and dive at any little ſtone throwne by a man at them, yet ſhrink not at the heavens great thunder: ſo many men are ſenſible enough, too ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible of any corporall danger to their per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, but too unſenſible of any ſpirituall danger to their profeſsion. As <hi>Bernard</hi> complain'd, <hi>Patientiùs ferimus Chriſti ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cturam, quàm noſtram,</hi> Many of us are leſſe ſenſible of Gods greateſt loſſes, than of
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:17662:43"/> the leaſt of our owne. That whereas <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broſe</hi> wont to wiſh, that if any troubles or harmes were to befall either Gods Church or him, they might rather of the two light upon him, and his houſe; ſo they may ſave their owne ſtakes, gaine their owne ends, many reckon ſo little of it, that what <hi>David</hi> if hee forgot, wiſh'd his right hand might forget to play, many men forget and play it out of minde, let it ſtray out of their memory: The Arke of God which ſhee grieving for, call'd the glory of Iſrael. Many men now are verie tender over the chariots of their owne glorie, but have little feeling of the Arke of Gods glory. As he complain'd that <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralus,</hi> the ſacred ſhip, was ſet a worke a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout triviall carriages; Chriſtian mens af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections which ſhould bee laid out about ſacred ſpirituall affaires, moſt men ſquan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der and trifle them away about ſecular vanities. Multitudes of men, either ſo be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſotted with carnall ſenſuality, or ſo be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numm'd with careleſſe ſecurity, or ſo en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>groſſed with covetous ſecularity, or ſo deaffed with the durdam of worldly vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; <hi>Neſcio quid teneros faſcinat,</hi> one thing or
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:17662:43"/> other ſo ſtupefying and deading all ſuch tendernes in us; many piping ſo many eies aſleep, ſearing ſo many conſciences, hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning ſo many through the deceitfulneſſe of ſinne, as that many men have little ſenſe of any ſpirituall hazzards, no feeling on that ſide; ſo deafe on that eare, that though not onely ſome <hi>Demetrius,</hi> but e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven a <hi>Mercurie,</hi> as they of Lycaonia call'd <hi>Paul,</hi> ſhould call unto us about it, we ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny liſt not heare, but like the Smiths dog, whom neither noiſe of hammers by him, nor ſparkes of fire flying about him, nor ſome lighting on him awaked. Many men lie ſtill, as not moved, nothing affected, as being that way paſt feeling, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, as <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaketh; as ſaying with the unſenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble man in <hi>Salomon, They have ſtricken mee and I was not ſicke, they have beaten mee and I felt it not:</hi> Or as <hi>Salomon</hi> tells of the ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple one, who as a foole unto the ſtockes, and as a bird haſting to the ſnare, not knowing that he is in danger, followed the harlot till a dart ſtroke through his li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver. Many men love to dally and foole with dangers, even ſpirituall dangers, the harlotry of ſinne, ſenſualitie, ſchiſme, ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtition,
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:17662:44"/> prophaneneſſe, till the dart ſtrike thorow the liver, the life of their Religion: whereas, as the Goſpell ſpeakes of the affectionate father, that whilſt the diſtreſſed ſonne was yet a great way off, he ſaw him and had compaſsion on him; were men heartily affected to God and his cauſe, the optick glaſſe of that affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, would repreſent to their compaſsion, any diſtreſſes of religion, even a great way off, and the ſpectacles of love would make any troubles at any time towards Gods cauſe, ſeeme unto them not leſſe, but hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pely greater, than in themſelves they are: affection would breed circumſpection, and the eare of iealouſie would make them both heare and hearken too after the ſtate and ſucceſſe of it; and a taſte of the powers of the world to come, would make men diſcerne any ſpirituall poyſon before they drinke it; and a tender reſpect to religion, would cauſe them ever rather caſt beyond than ſhort of any danger con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning it: having their ſenſes exerciſed, as <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeakes, to diſcerne good and evill about it, would make men ſhun not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the plague of any ſpirituall danger, but
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:17662:44"/> to bee ſhie even of every ragge that doth but touch upon it; to have a godly iealou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie over Gods whole cauſe, his Worſhip, his Church, his Children, and all the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequences of it. <hi>Non aliter</hi> (ſaies <hi>Beza</hi> of <hi>Calvin) non aliter in Eccleſias quantum vis re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>motas affectus, quàm ſi illas humeris geſtaret,</hi> That he had no leſſe tenderneſſe, no leſſe feeling even of remote Churches, than if he had borne them on his owne ſhoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders: A right Scholler of St. <hi>Pauls,</hi> who had a tender care, even over all the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, as <hi>Iſydor</hi> ſpake of him; looking after nothing elſe but the good of Gods Church. Whereas now (alas) as <hi>Paul</hi> ſpake, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>occalluerunt ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuſi ſenſus,</hi> mens ſpirituall ſenſes are oft<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten ſo blunted, their mindes are ſo much hardned, that as they ſay in nature, that the ſofter touch is a ſigne of the better conſtitution; mens hardneſſe of feeling this way, bewraies their badneſſe of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution: Nay, as Philoſophie ſaies, <hi>tactus fundamentum animae ſenſitivae.</hi> The very foundation of life to be feeling; and ſo no feeling, no life, ſaies <hi>Ariſtotle.</hi> Mens want of ſpirituall feeling, argues their want of
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:17662:45"/> ſpirituall life; as <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeakes of the wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton widow, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, that they are many that way but dead, even whilſt they live; many ſo unapprehenſive, ſo unaffected many, with what may trench upon God and his cauſe, that as ſome of the meaneſt creatures ſurpaſſe us in the outward touch, <hi>Praeſtat aranea tactu,</hi> ſo ſome of the worſt of men, ſeeme ſo to goe beyond many of us in inward feeling; that as <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon</hi> ſends the ſluggard to the poore Piſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mire, to conſider her waies and bee wiſe, we may many be ſent a ſchooling to theſe ſilly Idolaters here, as being many leſſe tender, leſſe touched with many things that concerne our glorious God, than they here were with what concern'd but their paltry <hi>Diana,</hi> when they cry'd thus out, ſaying, <hi>Great is Diana of the Epheſians:</hi> So have yee the firſt particular, their Ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſſe.</p>
            <p>Yea but for all this Tenderneſſe over their goddeſſe, loth that any winde of danger ſhould blow upon her, yet as <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſt</hi> ſaid once of the Romanes, <hi>Videmini in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenta mala quaſi fulmen, &amp;c.</hi> that they then ſeem'd to deale about their imminent
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:17662:45"/> harmes, as men doe about the thunder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bolt, every man willing it may not hit him, but no man going about to hinder it; it may be, for all they ſo perceiv'd her danger, yet went they not about to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent it. Yes, as hee wittily ſaid, that all ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hement affections, are (as it were) of a doubtfull ſexe, having <hi>impotentiam mulie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brem,</hi> but <hi>impetum virilem,</hi> with a wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maniſh feebleneſſe, a kinde of manly vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence; ſo together with that their ſoft, and as it were Feminine tenderneſſe, here's al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo their ſtout and Maſculine eagerneſſe on her behalfe, <hi>They cry'd out.</hi> Their Earneſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, that's now the ſecond particular propounded: For having once that reſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of their <hi>Diana's</hi> danger, they do not ſtand mute, no nor coldly call on, but Cry out, as if it were not enough to ſay ſo, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe they cry'd ſo, <hi>Exclamaverunt</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, as <hi>Phavorinus</hi> ſpeakes of the roote of this word, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, that it is a crying with keenneſſe and earneſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, as the Scholiaſt ſpeakes of that <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, that cry, that great cry in the 18. of <hi>Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſis,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, that it intimates there their ſtoutneſſe and boldneſſe; ſo
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:17662:46"/> theſe cryers here, <hi>furioſis vociferationibus ingeminantes,</hi> as ſome paraphraſe, redou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble it ſo with furious vociferations, that whereas within leſſe than an houre, the ſound of a Sermon here uſually growes tedious; the 34. verſe here ſaies, that for a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the ſpace of two houres, there was a ſhout, crying, <hi>Great is Diana.</hi> St. <hi>Chryſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome</hi> well expreſſes it, <hi>Ita afficiebantur quaſi vocibus cultum ejus reparaturi,</hi> That they were ſo tranſported with affection towards her, as to goe about with their very voices to uphold her honour, to car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry the cauſe with voices, and to blow up all oppoſition againſt her with their very breath, <hi>They cry'd out.</hi> Yea out of more keenneſſe yet, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, as ſome co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pies here have it, <hi>diſcurrentes per civitatem,</hi> ſo <hi>Comeſtor;</hi> running and even raving as it were, They cry'd out; that though ſuch tumultuous out-cries, the common re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſorts of raſh unruly people, <hi>clamoſi murmu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra vulgi,</hi> bee no patterne for Chriſtian profeſſors, amongſt the things that <hi>Paul</hi> would have put away from us, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4. this ſame <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>clamor,</hi> being one: yet as <hi>Iehu</hi> ſaid, <hi>Come ſee my zeale for the Lord,</hi>
               <pb n="85" facs="tcp:17662:46"/> ſee we but herein their zeale in their gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, and it will ſhame many of us in ours; as <hi>Ierome</hi> ſaid, <hi>Conſiderare pudet quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus fervor, quae cura, &amp;c.</hi> that he was aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to thinke how ſollicitous men are in ſecular things, and yet how ſluggiſh in ſpirituall things; <hi>Conſiderare pudet,</hi> may we likewiſe parallel it, it will make any ſpirituall minded man aſhamed to think that theſe Heathen wretches, ſhould bee ſo importunately clamorous and vocall in their curſed courſe, and many Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans ſo infatuatly dumbe and dull for their bleſſed profeſsion: they ſo fierce all for their cauſe, and many of us ſo faint for ours; they ſo ſtout, and many Chriſtians ſo ſqueamiſh, as ſcarce to dare to owne Gods cauſe, having no courage for the truth, as <hi>Ieremie</hi> complained. No better many than thoſe drie bones in <hi>Ezekiel,</hi> with ſinnewes, and fleſh, and skinne on them, but no breath, no life in them. But as <hi>Ierome</hi> ſaid of ſpirituall things, <hi>Pigrâ quâdam diſsimulatione negligimus,</hi> with a kinde of dull diſsimulation, many ſlight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and lightly paſsing by any matter of religion, whilſt theſe here ſo eagerly earne
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:17662:47"/> and cry out in maintenance of their ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtition. Or if wee can ſhift, or ſet light by this one inſtance in them, meet wee may with parallels to the ſame purpoſe in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny others; not only in godly perſons, who for Sions ſake could not hold their tongues, and for Ieruſalems ſake could not reſt, as in <hi>Eſay;</hi> &amp; as <hi>Ierome</hi> to <hi>Heliodore, Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cèt parvulus ex collo pendeat nepos, &amp;c.</hi> for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bearing neyther father, nor mother, nor kindred for Chriſts cauſe; pittying not ſonne, nor daughter, nor wife of their owne boſome, nor friend as their owne ſoule, but ſlaying them in Gods quarrell, <hi>Deut.</hi> 13. as when <hi>Levi</hi> ſaid unto his father and to his mother, <hi>I have not ſeene him:</hi> neither did hee acknowledge his owne brethren, nor knew his owne children, out of obſervance to the Word and Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant; even naturall affections giving place to ſpirituall affections, as more predo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minant in them. As <hi>Nazianzene</hi> ſaid, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>facillimus ferventiſsimus, &amp; manſuetus pugnax, &amp;c.</hi> the zeale of Gods cauſe making even the quieteſt of them keene, and the mildeſt of them eager and hote: as when the zeale of Gods houſe e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:17662:47"/> eat up <hi>David;</hi> and <hi>Paul</hi> readie not to be bound onely, but even to dye alſo for the Name of the Lord Ieſus; and <hi>Luther</hi> reſolved to enter <hi>Wormes</hi> in the Name of Chriſt, were there as many Devils as there were tyles to cover the houſes. As <hi>Calvin</hi> ſaid, <hi>Ne decem quidem maria, &amp;c.</hi> That it would not grieve him to ſaile over tenne Seas, about an uniforme draught for Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion: As <hi>Philo</hi> ſaid, <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>bi de religione, ibi quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que de vita agitur,</hi> holding even their verie lives to hold upon religion, ſerving God with all their might, as is commanded; readie to run even thorow fire and water for their holy profeſsion: Not onely in ſuch, I ſay, but even in their owne mates and fellow Idolaters, <hi>pro aris &amp; focis,</hi> they wont all to ſay, but <hi>aris</hi> before <hi>focis. Albi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus</hi> put out of his Chariot his verie wife and children, to make roome there for the Veſtall Virgins. In the ſacking of Troy, <hi>Aeneas</hi> is ſaid firſt to have exported <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, and then <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, to have carried forth his gods, even before his deareſt father. And about the Oracle and Temple, who hath not heard of the hote warres of the Athenians? Yea even in this their owne
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:17662:48"/> key and tune, for the worſhip of the gol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den Image in <hi>Daniel,</hi> the Herald cried with might and maine. The Chemarims in their ſacrifices, cryed with loud voyces: the Idolatrous Prieſts of <hi>Baal</hi> cryed aloud, as if <hi>Baal</hi> had beene aſleepe and needed waking, as <hi>Eliah</hi> mocked them; the Frogs in <hi>Homer</hi> that with their noyſe would not let the goddeſſe <hi>Pallas</hi> ſleepe, croaked no louder. Becauſe of the Calfe of Beth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aven, the inhabitants of Samaria feared, yea the people thereof mourned over it, &amp; the Prieſts for the glory thereof, becauſe it departed from it, <hi>Hoſe.</hi> 10. fearing and mourning, and much adoo about their I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doll. <hi>Feſtinant,</hi> ſaies <hi>David</hi> in the 16. <hi>Pſalm,</hi> They haſten after another God, very keen and quicke at that; following <hi>Baalim,</hi> they are like a ſwift Dromedary, that runneth by his waies, ſaies <hi>Ieremy. Acceleraverunt,</hi> as that 16. <hi>Pſalm</hi> mentioneth: Nay to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other God they offer and give gifts, as o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers reade it there. <hi>Dotant</hi> reads <hi>Tremellius</hi> there, they doe ſo dote upon their Idolls, that they doe not receive from them, but give a dowry to them; they offer and give gifts; nothing ſo coſtly which they will
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:17662:48"/> not beſtow upon them, nothing ſo hard which they will not endure for them: be it to burne and ſacrifice their owne chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren to them, to make ſonne or daughter goe through the fire to Moloch; bee it to pluck off from wives, and ſonnes, and daughters their golden earings in contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bution to a Calfe. How ready of old they have beene to do it, divine Story tells you; or if moderne practices may be more mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving, looke upon the Turkes eagerneſſe in defending &amp; propagating that their Law, <hi>Non diſputando, ſed pugnando,</hi> as <hi>Mahomet</hi> taught them; their ſtrict inquiſition and ſeverity towards neglecters of praiers, eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially in time of their Lent, and their Friday ſervices; their Largeſſes and boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties to Chriſtians converting to them, and all that other. Or if Chriſtian inſtances may be more operative, looke upon the Romaniſts, in the iudgement of ſome ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent men, <hi>Similes hi planè illis,</hi> very like to theſe Epheſians. What coſt caſt they not away upon their Images? what tedious pilgrimages doe they not trudge bare-foot to them? what whippings, and watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, and faſtings endure they not? Into
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:17662:49"/> what houſes creepe they not, thereby to leade captive ſilly women? what inſolent priviledges challenge they not, the verie Concubines of their Prieſts to bee of Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſticall iuriſdiction? what regall ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>premacie undermine they not? what mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving miracles coine they not? what Aſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſin have they not ſet on worke for their cauſe? what ſtone have they not moved? what earth have they not digged, even till hell beneath was moved to meete them? If I may ſo uſurp ſuch holy words, hedging, gathering, planting, building: what could they have done more for their wilde vine, that they have not done unto it? <hi>Per mare, per terras, per ſaxa, per ignes, tot volvere caſus, tot adire labores;</hi> as Chriſt ſpake of the Scribes and Phariſees com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſsing ſea and land to make a Proſelyte, one of their owne profeſsion, <hi>Quae regio in terris tanti non plena laboris?</hi> If there be any to whom the Syrens voice ſounds ſweete, hearken, their owne tongues ſhall teſtifie for them herein, their Ieſuites owne ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſsion ſhall evidence their earneſtneſſe. <hi>Campian</hi> in his Epiſtle to the honourable Counſellors of that renowned Queene
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:17662:49"/> 
               <hi>Elizabeth, Quamdiu vel unus quiſpiam è no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bis ſupererit, qui Tiburno veſtro fruatur, &amp;c.</hi> ſaies hee, That ſo long as there was any one Ieſuite of them remaining to enioy Tiburne; <hi>Fruatur,</hi> that's his word, to weare a Tiburne Typpet, as plaine M. <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timer</hi> was wont to ſpeake; ſo long as there was one of them left for the Gallowes, torment and impriſonment, they had vow'd never to deſiſt from endeavouring to draw us to that religion, <hi>Tantum relligio potuit ſuadere laborum.</hi> Their proverbiall ſaddle wont to bee ſet upon the Engliſh, were proofe apparent, how much our people wont to toile for that cauſe, and but ſumme up with Biſhop <hi>Iewell,</hi> the heavie multitude of payments and perqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſites, the Pope heretofore had out of this Land, &amp; the Proverbe will be eaſily belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, &amp; their keenneſſe for that cauſe, then notoriouſly manifeſted; the very Geeſe for the Capitoll not more vigilant, more vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call. If we liſt not to look backward on others, looke we but downe now upon our ſelves preſent, how carefull, and cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and keene wee are in worldly occur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences: If but a houſe bee on fire, there's
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:17662:50"/> crying out, <hi>Stentor</hi> cry'd no louder: if but our childe, or brother, or friend miſcarrie, there's bleating, crying upon crying, <hi>Cla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſſent ut littus Hyla Hyla omne ſonaret.</hi> As the ſonne of <hi>Croeſus,</hi> though formerly dumbe, is ſaid yet to have cry'd out in his fathers danger; we are not ſo dumbe, but that wee can finde tongue enough to cry out in many caſes of our owne cauſes: <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, as he ſpake, boyſtrous and ſwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling paſſions, impetuous enough, obſtre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perous enough, loude enough in ſecular paſſages; And ſhall then only we, and we onely in ſpirituall affaires, the matters of our God, even languiſh, be feeble &amp; flag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing often? <hi>Ferventiſsimi in terrenis, frigi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſsimi in coeleſtibus?</hi> Shal many of us, as in <hi>Ieremy,</hi> have tongues bent like Bowes for lyes, but not be valiant for the truth? Shall falſe weights ſet the wheeles of ſo manie other tongues a going, and we not be rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die to utter a word in due ſeaſon for the truth? <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, as <hi>Epiphanius</hi> phraſeth it, free-mouth'd for the truth of the Goſpell. Shall others drive, like <hi>Iehu,</hi> earneſtly, and we, like the Egyptians with their wheeles off, heavily? As tis obſerved
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:17662:50"/> of <hi>Iob,</hi> and his friends, that they had an ill cauſe in hand, but defended it craftily; and <hi>Iob</hi> a good cauſe to defend, but handled it unadviſedly. Shall Turkes, ſhall Papiſts, ſhall Idolaters, ſhall Heathen ſollicite their bad cauſe ſo earneſtly; and wee our good cauſe, our Gods cauſe ſo faintly? <hi>Acriùs ad perniciem, quàm nos ad ſalutem?</hi> As in that ſea-tempeſt the prophane Mariners cry'd every man unto his God, whilſt <hi>Ionah,</hi> the Lords Prophet, was gone downe into the ſides of the ſhip, and lay faſt aſleepe. Shall prophane men, ſhall Papiſticall men cla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour ſo for their woodden or breaden gods? and ſhall any of the houſhold of Faith by any ſluggiſhneſſe ſeeme to preiu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice and betray the cauſe of their great and glorious God? As when <hi>Callidus</hi> once declared againſt <hi>Gallus</hi> with a faint and languiſhing voice: O, ſaies <hi>Tullie, Tu niſi fingeres, ſic ageres?</hi> Wouldſt thou utter it ſo feebly if thou werſt in earneſt? Mens faint appearing for Gods cauſe gives ſhrewd ſuſpition that many do but feine; their coldneſſe for religion probably con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludes they doe but counterfeit; that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in tongue ſuch mutes for the true,
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:17662:51"/> they are many in heart conſonants to the falſe; hardly would hee lend religion his bloud, who liſt not ſpare it ſo much as his breath; hardly would he die for it, who will not ſo much as cry for it. For what though there bee a time, an evill time, when the prudent man ſhall keep ſilence, as in <hi>Amos?</hi> yet even in thoſe worſt times, that time of great and univerſall corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, <hi>They that feared the Lord, ſpake then e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very one to his neighbour, ſpake often one to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other, and the Lord hearkned and heard it, Malach.</hi> 3. And even when the iniquity of the houſe of Iſrael and Iudah was ſo excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding great, that the land was full of bloud, and the city of corrupt iudgement, yet even then Gods children mourn'd and cry'd for the abominations done in the midſt thereof, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 9. and their ſighes were then ſollicitors for their affections. That what though ſuch turbulent crying beſeeme not true Chriſtians? have they not in ſecret the voice of weeping with <hi>David?</hi> Have they not cry for cry? the cry of praier which goeth through the clouds, and ceaſeth not till it come nigh, and will not depart untill the moſt High
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:17662:51"/> have reſpect unto it; even wraſtling with God, and will not let him goe untill hee bleſſe his Church, his Cauſe, Religion. That as when <hi>Hannah</hi> powring out her ſoule before the Lord, ſpake in her heart, even when her voice was not heard; and when <hi>Moſes</hi> ſpake not a word vocally, yet ſaid the Lord unto him, <hi>Wherefore cryeſt thou unto mee?</hi> Wee may cry, and out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cry theſe even without crying out; it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing not with the true God, as hee ſaid of the falſe, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, that hee was to bee wooed and wrought upon with noiſe &amp; clamour: but even without this ſtrong winde wee may appeare before God, as God himſelfe appeared in the ſoft and ſtill voice; humbly begging a bleſsing upon re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion. As <hi>Bodin</hi> ſpake well of obtaining, ſo for retaining religion, <hi>Non diſputationi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus, ſed rogationibus,</hi> not ſo much by diſpu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation as devotion; not by vociferation, but praier; as I heard of a good Biſhop to ſpend foure houres a day in prayer to that purpoſe. I would we were all ſuch cryers out; otherwiſe be it never ſo true which is commented here, and wherewith cold profeſſors are ready ever and anon
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:17662:52"/> to cloake themſelves: That great is the difference betweene the diſtempered paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of ſome phantaſtique men, and the diſcreet zeale of ſober men; between tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulent fancy, and true ſanctity; betweene the winde of giddineſſe, and the ſpirit of holineſſe; between the buſling and noyſe of thoſe who are yet but about the doore of religion, and the moderation and ſtil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of thoſe who are got within; as <hi>Plutarch</hi> wittily ſpake of Philoſophy. And many of the ſame Cryers out like <hi>Cyclops</hi> roring without his eye, attempting things with great tumult and no iudgement; and many hot blouds having but cold di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcretion, and all that other, for all that bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome idoll of diſcretion; unleſſe our ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtneſſe equalize, nay as Chriſt ſaid, <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept your righteouſneſſe exceed the righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the Scribes and Phariſees,</hi> except our earneſtneſſe this way exceed the ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtneſſe of theſe and thoſe other like men; <hi>Si non praeſtet fides, quod exhibuit infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delitas,</hi> as <hi>Ierom</hi> ſaid, If faith make not us (at leaſt) as forward and keen for Gods cauſe, as infidelitie here made them for theirs, <hi>Haec in ſugillationem noſtri dicta ſint,</hi>
               <pb n="97" facs="tcp:17662:52"/> as he ſpake, to our utter diſcredite and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>famy be it ſaid, They cryed out, ſaying: <hi>Great is Diana of the Epheſians.</hi> So have yee the ſecond particular, their Earneſtneſſe.</p>
            <p>Nor was this crying out here, the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nology of ſome one odde one, no nor the impetuous paſsion, the furious ſalley of ſome few hot ſpurs amongſt them; but the cry of them all, none here excepted, a common crying out, as for a common cauſe, that their keenneſſe backt with conſent: Their Ioyntneſſe, thats now in this firſt part, the third and laſt particular. As all of them were called together about the danger, ſo all of them cryed together in the defence: the following verſe ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming to ſecond this obſervation of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, where it ſaies <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, that for all the citie was then full of confuſion, yet ruſh'd they into the common place with one aſſent, <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>no animo:</hi> and though in the aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembly out of order, ſome cry'd one thing, ſome another, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, yet to this point about <hi>Diana's</hi> defence, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, ſaies the 34. verſe, <hi>Vox vna omnium,</hi> they cry'd all with one voyce, all in a tune; eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally theſe companions here in the Text,
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:17662:53"/> 
               <hi>Clamaverunt vnanimiter,</hi> ſaies <hi>Comeſtor,</hi> A ioynt cry of the whole croud of them: <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cios artis aſſumit ſocios tumultus,</hi> ſo <hi>Chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoſtome:</hi> As many as were fellowes of that company, were alſo ioynt fellowes of that crying out. A frequent coniunction, as in theſe, ſo in other like people <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>; as <hi>David</hi> ſpeakes in the 83. Pſalme, <hi>vna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimiter ſimul,</hi> With one conſent to conſult together and bee confederate; as in the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venth of this Booke, to run upon <hi>Steven</hi> with one aſſent; as in the Chapter before this, to riſe againſt <hi>Paul</hi> with one accord; to ſay as in <hi>Salomon, Come with us, caſt in thy lot amongst us, we will all have one purſe;</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeing like theeves in a Faire, all ſharers: the congregation of the wicked like towe wrap'd together, ſaies <hi>Eccleſiaſticus;</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pact and ſealed like the <hi>Leviathans</hi> ſcales in <hi>Iob,</hi> as they are reſembled. As the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>Micah</hi> likens the wicked to briers; and <hi>Nahum</hi> to thornes folded one in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, they clap and twine and enterweave themſelves, as birds of a feather they fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently fly together; and as in conſort of communion ioyntly here cryed out. And ſhall ſuch brethren in evill tune ſo like
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:17662:53"/> bells, and want but hanging (as he ſaid?) ſhall Sathans kingdome be at ſuch agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment within it ſelfe that it may endure? &amp; ſhall Chriſtians that profeſſe one Lord, one Fath, one Baptiſme, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, as in <hi>Paul,</hi> a threefold cord which a man would thinke could not eaſily bee broken: wee that have one word as one breath from one ſpirit, as <hi>Dionyſius</hi> ſpeakes; wee that have the ſame temples and ſacrifices, as the Athenians alledged; wee that are e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpouſed to one husband, as <hi>Paul</hi> ſpake of the Corinthians; ſhall wee be ſo carnall as to have amongſt us envying and ſtrife and diviſion, and one to ſay, I am of <hi>Paul,</hi> and another, I am of <hi>Apollo;</hi> and like the diviſions of <hi>Reuben,</hi> cauſe great thought of heart? Shall theſe here have <hi>vnitatem contra vnitatem?</hi> ſhall there be ſuch con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiracy in error? and ſhal there not be u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie in truth? If ye eye and obſerve but this Booke of the Acts, yee ſhall finde the veine of thoſe primitive Chriſtians to run all along <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>chap.</hi> 1. <hi>&amp;</hi> 2. <hi>&amp;</hi> 4. ever and anon one accord, one aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent to be ſpecified in them; and ſhal we, riſen up in their ſtead, a worſe generation,
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:17662:54"/> ſo run after the apple of diſcord, the ball of contention, and ſo agree like the Brick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>layers at Babell? that as diviſion of tongues hindred the building then, ſo di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion of hearts hinder the building of Chriſtianitie now. For, conferre with the Iew; one of the maine ſcandals the Iewes take from Proteſtants, is their mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall diſſention; which they interprete to proceed from want of unitie of truth in their foundation; and ſo they thereby are ſtartled and ſcared from the Goſpell. Come neerer, what ſayes the Papiſt to like purpoſe? heare but one for all (one of them is enough, unleſſe they were bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter): heare but their <hi>Bartholdus;</hi> What one of the Heretickes (ſayes hee) preaches in the morning, another of them denies after dinner; and what peace, what ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord in that houſe (ſayes hee) where the husband is a Calviniſt, the wife a Luthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ran, the ſerving-man an Oecolampadian, the maid Pittardicall, and the reſt of the family Diabolicall? So charitably their <hi>Bartholdus Pontanus.</hi> We could pay them in their owne coyne, by telling them, and that truely, that their white and blacke
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:17662:54"/> Friars differ as much in opinion as colour, and Harpe and Harrow as conſonant as many of them. But I ſhall never hold re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crimination for a remedie: this muſt I hold, (as they ſay of Bees) that ſtirre and ſtrife among them is a ſigne their King is about to remove, to leave the Hive, and to be gone ſomewhere elſe: ſo ſtrife and ſchiſme in religion to be a ſigne, God ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hath, or is about to leave that people. Boords ioyned make a Ship, diſ-ioyned they cauſe ſhipwracke; connexion of ſtones make a houſe, diſsipation of them a ruine; agreement of Chriſtians builds up the ſpiritual Ieruſalem, diſſention of them puls it downe. The daughter of diſſenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is diſſolution, ſaid divine <hi>Nazianzene:</hi> and that which is diviſible is corruptible, even Nature dictates: and every ſubdivi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion in cauſe of Religion, is a ſtrong wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon in the hand of the contrary partie; as hee upon the Councell of Trent wiſely obſerved. The wiſedome of <hi>Solon,</hi> when Athens was diſtracted into three facti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, <hi>Diacriorum, Pedeorum, Paralorum,</hi> his civill wiſedome could dictate unto him, to mingle himſelfe with none of the ſides,
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:17662:55"/> but to direct all his ſayings and doings towards common concord. O that there were in Chriſtian people ſuch a wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, ſuch a heart, as without ſiding to apply all their words and workes to the common good of Gods cauſe, Religion. As the Scripture ſpeakes of <hi>David,</hi> that hee bowed the hearts of all the men of Iudah, even as the heart of one man; that under our <hi>David</hi> all our hearts, as of one man, were bent and ioyned for Gods cauſe, for the Goſpell: Then, as hee ſaid, that ſhield ioyning to ſhield, helmet to helmet, man to man, was a ſufficient wall. For to him that demanded why Sparta had no wals, the King ſhewed Citizens well armed and unanimous: in ſuch unanimitie reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion would both be impregnably wall'd on earth; and as the petition of a whole Corporation ioyntly, uſes to be more a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaileable, our prayer, our crying for it would be more effectuall in heaven; and when all is ſaid and done, as the learned <hi>Papinian</hi> ſaid, <hi>Summa ratio eſt quae pro Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gione facit,</hi> That that was the beſt reaſon which made moſt for Religion, our ſweeteſt harmony would bee conſent in
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:17662:55"/> Gods cauſe, our trueſt valour courage for the truth, our beſt conſtitution tender<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe over religion: That as Maſter <hi>Lati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer</hi> in a Sermon before King <hi>Edward,</hi> made ſupplication, that they would con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribute as bountifully towards the find<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of ſchollers, to exerciſe the office of ſalvation, as they wont to beſtow in pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grimage, trentals, maſſes, pardons, pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatory matters, as he there expounds him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe; he deſired no more, but that they would beſtow ſo much godly, as they were wont to beſtow ungodly: a reaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable petition, as he then call'd it; ſo mee thinks, no reaſonable man now can refuſe to be intreated, to be once (at leaſt) as ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, as earneſt, as united for the holy cauſe, as theſe here were for the heatheniſh; at the cheapeſt, to hold God as deare as they did <hi>Diana.</hi> Otherwiſe, as God in <hi>Eſay</hi> rebukes Iſrael even from the verie oxe and aſſe; and in <hi>Ieremie</hi> Iudah from the ſtorke and turtle, and crane and ſwallow; and Chriſt ſaid, that the Queene of the South ſhould riſe in iudgement with that generation and condemn it: theſe verie Idolaters ſhall rebuke and riſe in iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:17662:56"/> with this generation, and condemn it: and as Wiſedome ſaid, That the Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cho rebounding from the mountaines made the wicked to ſwoune; the neglec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of the divine cauſe ſhall one day bee checked and confounded with the Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cho of this cry for <hi>Diana's</hi> cauſe, when they cryed thus out, ſaying:
<q>Great is Diana of the Epheſians.</q>
            </p>
            <closer>Laus Deo.</closer>
         </div>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="105" facs="tcp:17662:56"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>It followeth ACTS 19.28.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>And cryed out, ſaying, Great is Diana of the Epheſians.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S <hi>Pliny</hi> ſpake of that viſage of <hi>Diana, Intrantes triſtem, exeun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes exhilaratum putant,</hi> that to the commers in it ſeemed ſad &amp; penſive, but to the goers out looked blithe and cheerefull: ſo may I ſay of this Text of <hi>Diana, Intranti ſterilis, exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unti foecundus,</hi> at firſt entrance might it ſeeme barren, but upon further examina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion proves ſo fruitfull, that like thoſe ſheepe in the <hi>Canticles,</hi> it bringeth out Twins; the one holding the other by the heele, as in <hi>Geneſis.</hi> The firſt that came out was the travell, <hi>They cryed out:</hi> That which now is to come forth, is the Babie (the Brat, if you will) <hi>Diana.</hi> The for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer was the Prologue, <hi>They cryed out;</hi> and now followes the Fable, <hi>Great is Diana.</hi> The maner went before, <hi>They cryed out;</hi>
               <pb n="106" facs="tcp:17662:57"/> the matter now comes after, <hi>Great Diana.</hi> The <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> was, <hi>They cryed out, ſaying;</hi> the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> is, <hi>Great is Diana of the Epheſians.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In ſurvay wherof, leſt the diſcourſe of this matter of their cry prove now as confuſed as did that maner of their crying, when it fill'd the whole city with confuſion, as fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth here, I chuſe againe, in correſpon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence to <hi>Diana's</hi> triformitie, <hi>diva triformis,</hi> as ſhe is called, to caſt theſe three wordes here <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, (if that word bee not here unacceptable) into theſe three inquiſitions: firſt, to make inquiry what this ſame partie, for whom all this clamor and ſtirre here was; what ſhee was in her ſelfe, why, <hi>Diana.</hi> Secondly, to examine what ſhe was here to others, why, <hi>Great; Great Diana.</hi> And thirdly, who theſe here were that had this great conceit of her, why, <hi>Epheſians, Great Diana of the Epheſians.</hi> So as <hi>Iſidore</hi> ſpake once of the Serpent, <hi>Tot dolores, quot colores:</hi> ſo many parts here, ſo many prevarications: That what hee Chriſtianly ſpake, <hi>Tantus, tantum, pro tantil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis,</hi> we may invert and turne it here, <hi>Tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tilla, tanta, apud tantos;</hi> that one ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temptible as <hi>Diana,</hi> in the eſtimate of men
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:17662:57"/> ſo underſtanding as Epheſians, ſhould mount to ſuch valuation as greatneſſe, wil proue proportionate to Romiſh parallels, matter of more wonder than worth, more worthie of our ſcorning than their crying
<q>Great is Diana of the Epheſians.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt then, <hi>Diana,</hi> for whom all this adoe here was, what was ſhee? <hi>Quid tanto dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num hiatu?</hi> Why, to begin withall, none of the more worthy gender, but feminine ſhe was, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>haec Diana,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, as thriſe in the context here for ſureneſſe; not god, but goddeſſe. As if, as we uſe to ſay, that ſinnes like loſſes, come huddle, by doublets; and as <hi>Tertullian</hi> ſaid of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>enus</hi> and <hi>Bacchus,</hi> luſt and drunkenneſſe, <hi>Duo iſta Daemonia conſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rata &amp; conjurata,</hi> that them two Devils went ever in the couples: ſo it were not divelliſh enough for Heatheniſh Idolatry to multiply number of gods, unleſſe it vary gender too; not incongruitie enough, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Serpents Grammar, <hi>Deum pluraliter declinare,</hi> as <hi>Damianus</hi> ſpeakes, to decline God plurally, <hi>Eritis ſicut Dij,</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe it thus decline him femally too, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Dea, Diana.</hi> That whereas they ſay, Wit whither wilt thou? we may ſay of them,
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:17662:58"/> Wickedneſſe whither wilt thou? from e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill to worſe, from gods to goddeſſes. A frequent falſification amongſt thoſe Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then then: Nor is it yet altogether anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quated, nor quite worne out amongſt Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maniſts now, whilſt howſoever <hi>Bellar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine,</hi> and ſo <hi>Binius,</hi> like drowning men, that catch hold of any reed or ruſh to helpe them, ſet downe that as a pregnant diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence betweene Heatheniſh Idols and Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh Images, That the Heathen thus re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſented feminine gods, <hi>quales dij, nec ſunt, nec eſſe poſſunt,</hi> (ſayes <hi>Bellarmine</hi>) gods of ſuch kind as neyther are, nor ever can be. As if there could bee ſome gods in time which be not yet. For all that their maſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culine profeſsion, looke but into their fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minine practiſe, and then ſee and ſay, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the ſhoo which <hi>Hiſtiaeus</hi> made, <hi>Ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtogaras</hi> doth not weare; whether <hi>Diana's</hi> buskin will not ſomewhat fit their Dei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties; whether as of old <hi>Aricinus Lacus</hi> was called <hi>Speculum Dianae:</hi> ſo this Text of <hi>Diana</hi> may not in ſome ſort be called <hi>Spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culum Romae;</hi> whether as their owne <hi>Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinus</hi> reſembles <hi>Diana's</hi> ſhrines here, to the Images of their Lauretto Chappell there,
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:17662:58"/> there be not ſome reſemblance, ſome affi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity betwixt theſe and them: whether, as a great Light of theſe late times calls the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion that ſtands in force by the Councell of Trent, the great and famous Italian <hi>Diana;</hi> Italian Rome taſt not ſtill of this ſame cask of <hi>Diana:</hi> whether, as <hi>Bernard</hi> taxd the ſingers in his time, <hi>Muliebre, non virile,</hi> that they ſung womaniſh, their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion fancy not the feminin, leane not much thus towards <hi>Diana:</hi> witnes their divine Ladie, ſhe for whom the mighty hath done great things, their Queen of Heaven, the bleſſed Virgin, a Heavenly Saint ſure, metamorphiſed to a god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſſe; yet ſo, that whereas <hi>Campian</hi> prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed <hi>Wenceſlaus,</hi> that hee caus'd not <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerva,</hi> but <hi>Maria</hi> to bee adored: for all their adoring, they have often ſeemed rather to have turned <hi>Maria</hi> to <hi>Minerva.</hi> To ſhew but a peece for a patterne; looke but upon the Story of their Fryar <hi>Allen,</hi> betrothed to the bleſſed Virgin, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a Ring made of a lock of her own haire, and much more ribaldry than modeſty may mention in this preſence, and then ſay ingeniouſly, whether yee thinke they
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:17662:59"/> ſpeake of holy Mary, or not rather of ſome Heatheniſh Minerva: of a Minerva born of their owne brain, rather than the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Mary. And to that ribaldry of ſome of them, annex that blaſphemy of other of them that way too: When Chriſt ſaying, <hi>Eſay</hi> 63. <hi>I have troden the winepreſſe alone, and of all people, there was no man with mee:</hi> True Lord, ſay ſome of them, there was then no man with thee, but there was a woman: Not good that man ſhould bee alone, as they ſport with the Scripture, but a helpe with him: <hi>Maria adjutrix no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrae redemptionis,</hi> ſo their <hi>Benhardinus; Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocata,</hi> ſo <hi>Antonius. Advocatum habemus,</hi> ſaies S. <hi>Iohn; Advocatam,</hi> ſay they: <hi>Vnus Mediator,</hi> ſaies S. <hi>Paul; Mediatrix,</hi> ſing they: <hi>Dominus illuminator,</hi> ſaies <hi>Salomon; illuminatrix,</hi> ſay they: <hi>Deus auxiliator,</hi> ſaies <hi>Eſay; auxiliatrix,</hi> ſay they. Not without ſome ſmell of this ſame garlick mortar, not without a ſpice, a tang this way of <hi>Diana.</hi> The Diuinity of their femall pope ſilly <hi>Ione,</hi> the ſtrange, but true parallel to this feminine Deity of <hi>Diana:</hi> Thus not to touch more of that pitch, their <hi>Ordo me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritricum,</hi> founded by <hi>Tiſceranus</hi> the Mino<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit,
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:17662:59"/> their new ſet up <hi>Ieſuitrices, &amp;c.</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out raveling of the worſt, wind I it up with <hi>Eraſmus, Blandientes ſexui foemineo, &amp;c.</hi> Whether it be as they pretend in pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Virgin Mary, that they conceiue of Chriſt as a ſtrict and ſeuere Iudge, but of the Virgin as a milde and gentle advo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cat: (As if ſome other could bee more tender over us, than hee that dy'd for us.) Or which I rather beleeue, purpoſely to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſinuat with the credulous ſex, ſo to devour widowes houſes, to leade captive ſimple women, or ſerpent-like to vent tentations by the woman, to read many riddles by plowing with thoſe heiffers, or to worke their ſiniſter ends by the weaker veſſell; or whatſoever the Romiſh meaning be: that which <hi>Iuſtin Martyr</hi> miſlik'd in <hi>Homers</hi> Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>etry <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, being exemplified in their practice, verie womaniſh are they, verie free and forward have they long time bin, thus to magnifie, yea for a need thus to dei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie their <hi>Diana's.</hi> That as he once bid his hearers take heed of the Zuinglians hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, ſeeing there they had ſet <hi>Hercules</hi> with his club; a man has reaſon to bee ſhy both of the Ethnicall and Pontificiall heaven,
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:17662:60"/> wherein the diſtaff bears ſuch ſway: That whereas their <hi>Martinus</hi> ſaid, <hi>Se non optare ſibi coelum in quo Lutherus eſſet,</hi> that <hi>Martin</hi> would not wiſh for that Heaven where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in Luther was: ſo I never wiſh to bee of that religion here, nor goe to that heaven hereafter, wherein ſuch <hi>Diana's,</hi> goddeſſes are. In the kingdome of God I ſhall ſee <hi>Abraham, Iſaac, Iacob,</hi> the glorious compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of the Apoſtles, the goodly fellowſhip of the Prophets, the noble army of Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs, but ſhall ſee no goddeſſes, none of theſe <hi>Diana's</hi> there. Then let others thus wander after their owne inventions, ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginary goddeſſes, but, as <hi>David</hi> ſpake <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, let us adhere, hold faſt unto our iealous God: for bee the gods of the Heathen good-fellowes, as he ſaid, the true God is a iealous God, &amp; will not ſhare his glory with another. In the Booke of <hi>Kings</hi> the Seventy, for <hi>Dea</hi> reade <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, for goddeſſe abomination: let that mother of harlots have in her hand a cup full of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bominations and fornication, as in the <hi>Revelation;</hi> but <hi>take wee the cup of ſalvation</hi> (with <hi>David) and call upon the Name of the Lord,</hi> knowing, we cannot drinke the cup
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:17662:60"/> of the Lord, and the cup of Divells, as <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaketh. Let us tremble before the Maieſty of that glorious God, that hath his way in the whirlwinde, at whoſe reproofe the pillars of heaven tremble and quake, whilſt others trifle thus with their deviſed Deities: Let us ſay with <hi>David, Great is the Lord, and greatly to be praiſed,</hi> whilſt others cry thus <hi>Great Diana:</hi>
               <q>Great is Diana of the Epheſians.</q>
            </p>
            <p>As a femall, ſo a woman, this <hi>Diana</hi> was; but what manner of woman might ſhee be? It were not worth the beating of the buſh, to range through all the woods and groves of the Heathen, to bolt out all their <hi>Diana's</hi> upon every high hill, and under e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very green tree. <hi>Dianae plures,</hi> ſaies <hi>Tully, Diana's</hi> divers there were. A man may wink and chooſe of them, it matters not which of them it was; all of them were nought. He that has little to doe, let him but turne <hi>Pauſanias,</hi> hee ſhall finde there a litter, a whole kennell of them; <hi>Diana</hi> the huntreſſe, <hi>Diana</hi> the midwife, and the reſt of that multitude there: But among the whole beavie of their <hi>Diana's, Vna notiſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma,</hi> one famous, one above all the reſt:
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:17662:61"/> of whom <hi>Ierom,</hi> and others interpret this, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>multimammiam</hi> they call her, a kind of nurſe of things; <hi>Epheſia mammis multis &amp; verubus exſtructa,</hi> wrote <hi>Foelix; vberi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus exſtructa,</hi> as <hi>Lypſius</hi> happily help'd it: Well, and what was the ſame goodly one? The <hi>Sampſaei</hi> in <hi>Epiphanius</hi> worſhipt two women as goddeſſes, becauſe they were of the bleſſed ſeed, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, but was <hi>Diana</hi> ſo? no, by their own records, come of a curſed race, a baſtard daughter be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween <hi>Iupiter</hi> the adulterer, as themſelves ſtile him, and <hi>Latona</hi> the drab, <hi>Pellex,</hi> as I finde her ſtiled: the ſeed ſo of the adulterer and the whore, an honeſt genealogy ſure. At the beſt hand <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, as <hi>Clemens</hi> ſpake of all their gods, <hi>ſerva vitiorum,</hi> ſhee was ſome chambermaide to vice, ſome light huſwife, or ſo, or elſe lighter than ſo: in naked truth, <hi>ſine veſte Diana,</hi> ſtrip her but of fond fables, and for all the image com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming downe from <hi>Iupiter,</hi> as they fable here in the 35. verſe, wee ſhall then finde her, <hi>non Iovis, ſed Phydiae,</hi> as one ſaid of <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerva; Diana,</hi> not ſo of <hi>Latona,</hi> but ſome Lapidary, ſome ſtone or ſtock; as good blocks as ſhe, lying on the back of the fire, warming
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:17662:61"/> a man or roaſting meat, as in <hi>Eſay,</hi> or boyling <hi>Diagoras</hi> his turneps, <hi>inutile lignum maluit eſſe deum,</hi> or els ſom vain ſtone made by the hand of antiquitie, as <hi>Wiſdome</hi> men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions; happely as good ſtone trampled and troden under feet, nay yet lower, to bee e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven nothing: <hi>Idolum nihil eſt,</hi> an Idoll be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing nothing in the world, as <hi>Paul</hi> ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth. Great <hi>Diana</hi> come downe to this? a block or a blank nothing? Such a birth of the mountaines prove a mouſe? Such a clamour about a <hi>Diana</hi> of clouts? Such a deale of doo about nothing? All this bruit and no fruit? All this crying and no wool? I deny not, but (as <hi>Ignatius</hi> men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions) <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>mysteria clamoris,</hi> miſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries there be to be cry'd aloud and ſpare not; the voyce to be lifted up like a trum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pet, as in <hi>Eſay;</hi> to bee preached upon the houſe tops, as in the Goſpell; and we that are the Lords Remembrancers not to keep ſilence, for Sions ſake not to hold our tongues, and for Ieruſalems ſake not to reſt. <hi>Et vae mihi, quia tacui,</hi> as <hi>Eſay:</hi> Wo un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to me, becauſe I have held my peace, alas, will one day come to be the cry of many men, for not crying now; when not cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:17662:62"/> out in ſly diſcretion now, ſhall make many howle in deepe damnation then; when in bitterneſs of ſoule they ſhall wiſh (too late) they had beene borne dumb, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther than in Gods cauſe not to have cryed out: Yet were it but for this one inſtance about <hi>Diana</hi> here alone, I ſhall hardly ever credit popular out-cryes; As ſoone ſhall I meaſure wiſedome by the acre, as worth by noiſe, or piety by paſsion, or holineſſe by eagerneſſe, or religion by multitude, or truth by crying: This I perceive being cuſtomary with men conſcious of defects, to betake themſelves to clamor, as the lame man to his horſe: This the cuſtome of pleaſure, concupiſcence, and the like, with intenſive clamours to importune their deſires, as <hi>Philo</hi> ſaies; yea, even in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious affaires, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, as hee ſaid: This the cuſtome thus to make out-cryes their greateſt defences, as the Margeant there well noteth. Were ſuch exclamation demonſtration, would crying ſo carry the cauſe, Proteſtancy might hang her harps upon the willowes, the Romaniſts would quickly have the day; who (as Chriſt ſpake of vaine and ſuperſtitious repetitions
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:17662:62"/> in praying) thinke to bee heard for their much babling, they looke to bee beleeved for their much bawling: ſo frequent in their falſe hallows, that as hee ſaid of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quin,</hi> that that dumbe oxe ſhould bellow ſo loud, that all the world ſhould heare it: The world rings all of the bellowing of their bulls, the thunder of their excommu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nications, the clamour of their importuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, <hi>Tot tintinnabula dicas, tubas atque aera fatigant;</hi> as having that mouth which no adverſary is able to reſiſt, as they boaſt themſelves. But why boaſt yee ſo of po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pular concurrence, and keenneſſe, and cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing? <hi>Noſtrae virgines, noſtri ſeniculi,</hi> all <hi>noſtri</hi> if <hi>Campian</hi> may only reckon; Too too ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny indeed, the more is the pity, for that cauſe crying out. As if we knew not this, that little matters are often thus managed with great motions: Are there not vaine trifles ſollicited thus with vehement en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours? doe not the drones, though they make neither hony nor wax, make yet more noyſe than the bees? doe not ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thus dive deepe, and bring up nought but ſhells? may not the greater Quire be the worſe ſingers, as <hi>Zeno</hi> ſaid? may not
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:17662:63"/> multitude of aſſociats demonſtrate a He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retique, rather than a Catholique, as <hi>Ierom</hi> ſpake? may not the multitude periſh that are borne in vaine, as ſaid the Lord to <hi>Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dras?</hi> why, it may bee but a reed ſhaken with the winde, and yet many goe out to ſee it: it may be but a calfe, and yet people mourne over it, and kiſſe it, as in <hi>Hoſea:</hi> it may bee but iugling and impoſture, and yet the cry goe Miracles, Miracles: the cry may favour not Chriſt, but <hi>Barrabbas:</hi> it may bee but a deſpicable <hi>Diana,</hi> and yet there be crying thus out for it: <hi>Great is Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ana.</hi> But as concerning them that were puffed up, <hi>Paul</hi> cared not to know <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, but <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, not their ſpeech, but their power (as hee ſaid) not <hi>vociferationes,</hi> but <hi>rationes,</hi> not <hi>clamorem,</hi> but <hi>vigorem.</hi> Brethren, bee we never carried away with the Adverſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries importunity, or keenneſſe, or crying; but conſider wee the cauſe. Strong crying is but a weake proofe, and like water, of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten thus bears up light things, and lets the weightie ſinke: Then weake is hee, who (as light things upon the face of waters, <hi>non eunt, ſed feruntur</hi>) goes not of himſelfe, but as he is carried away by others. If one
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:17662:63"/> of their Mountebanks cry Balme, thou wilt try it, I trow, before thou truſt; and then the balme of Gilead, Religion, wilt thou take it up upon a raſh truſt? periſh upon credit? be captivated with any their quackſalvers crying? Nay, ſaith St <hi>Auſtine</hi> well, let never theſe words bee heard a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt us; I ſay, or thou ſayeſt, but looke what the Lord ſaith. As God ſaies in the 8. of <hi>Eſay,</hi> when they ſhall ſay unto you, Enquire at the ſoothſayers; ſhould not a people enquire at their God? will you en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cline to their crying, or will you not en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire at Gods ſaying? Yes, ſpeake Lord, thy ſervant heareth, as <hi>Samuel</hi> ſaid: other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, cry who they will, and what they will, To the law and to the teſtimony: if they ſpeake not according to that word, there is no light in them. A decree may come out from them, as of old in <hi>Tertul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian,</hi> None to be conſecrated god without the Senats approbation: but as the true God, though men approve him not, is yet a proofe unto himſelfe, ſo theſe falſe gods, though never ſo cry'd up, and approu'd of men, are not yet to bee acknowledged: That though Iſrael play the harlot, yet let
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:17662:64"/> not Iudah ſinne; ſuch cries of others muſt not call us after, nor may we follow mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titudes ſo to evill. Though hundreds cry <hi>Baal,</hi> call thou upon the Lord with <hi>Eliah:</hi> though others ſerve the gods of the <hi>Amo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rites,</hi> thou and thy houſe ſerve the Lord with <hi>Ioſuah:</hi> defie thou all ſtrange gods, though all <hi>Epheſus</hi> deifie <hi>Diana,</hi> crying:
<q>Great is Diana of the Epheſians.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Why, but what if <hi>Diana</hi> were never ſo baſe in her ſelfe? yet might ſhee thus paſſe for great with others, <hi>Great Diana:</hi> that is now the ſecond part. As <hi>Theognis</hi> to his purpoſe ſpake once to <hi>Diana, Tibi parvum, mihi magnum,</hi> though it be little to thee, tis great to mee: though ſo deficient and fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble in her ſelfe, as not able to defend her owne houſe from firing, burnt when ſhee was a goſsipping at <hi>Alexanders</hi> birth; a great Temple yet muſt ſhe have: <hi>Magnifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>centiae admiratio,</hi> ſaid <hi>Plinie</hi> of it, One of the 7. wonders of the world, 425. foote long, 220. foot broad, &amp;c. no leſſe would fit her greatneſſe. They never mention her here but with addition of greatneſſe, her magnificence, the great goddeſſe, &amp;c. As he ſpake of <hi>Molon</hi> the dwarf, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tillus
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:17662:64"/> quantus?</hi> ſo little in her ſelfe, yet thus great to others; <hi>Great Diana.</hi> So true is that of <hi>Tacitus, Satis clarus eſt apud timentem quiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quis timetur,</hi> There is none ſo meane, but is mighty to him that ſtands in awe of him; not only the Stork, but the very ſtock, a king to the frogs ſo long as they feare it; in no caſe more evidently true, than in this of Idolatry, wherein men overawde them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, not onely with the worſt of the rati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onall ranke, <hi>deos facitis criminociſsimos quoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que,</hi> as <hi>Tertullian</hi> told them; making gods of the moſt ungodly men, and left many honeſter men in hell (ſaies hee) than thoſe they hoyſted up to Heaven, worſhipping even Devills, as the <hi>Revelation</hi> mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth. No, nor onely with the meaneſt in the heard ſenſitive, Miſe as the Muſorits, ſerpents as the Ophits, ſheepe as the Saits, goates as the Mendeſii, &amp;c. <hi>volucreſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> poſuere deos:</hi> not only deifying <hi>Erigo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne,</hi> but leſt the wench ſhould bee ſad for lack of her dogge, placing her very dogge in heaven too, as hee well twitted <hi>Iupiter:</hi> nor yet onely with the vileſt of the troupe vegetable, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, as in <hi>Iuſtin Martyr,</hi> worſhipping even trees; but beneath the
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:17662:65"/> loweſt degree of life, worſhipping inferi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our degrees of nature, &amp; art, Idols of gold, ſilver, braſſe, ſtone, wood, as in the <hi>Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation:</hi> ready to ſay to a tree, Thou art my father, and to a ſtone, Thou haſt begotten me, as in <hi>Ieremy:</hi> to aske counſell at their ſtocks, and their ſtaff declareth unto them, as in <hi>Hoſea:</hi> to hew downe wood, and with ſome of it to bake, and with ſome of it to roſt, and of the reſidue to make a god, and bow to it, as in <hi>Eſay:</hi> and ſay, Deliver mee, for thou art my god, &amp;c. as that it made <hi>Lactantius</hi> wondring, queſtion the madnes of it, <hi>Quae amentia, &amp;c.</hi> What mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes it was for men to feign that, which af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards they would feare, or to feare that which formerly they had feigned, <hi>vſque adeone times quod tu facis ipſe timendum?</hi> like little children, ſtarting at thoſe viſages, which they themſelves black'd and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſmear'd; magnifying thus that which themſelves knew of how meane ingredi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ents it was made. <hi>Lapides lapidum cultores,</hi> as <hi>Rupertus</hi> ſpake: Things which had they ſenſe, would magnifie the men that made them, ſaies <hi>Lactantius:</hi> for men to bee ſo ſenſleſſe, as thus to magnifie thoſe things,
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:17662:65"/> ſurely they that make them are like unto them, and ſo are all they that put their truſt in them. <hi>Et qui, quaeſo, eorum non miſerearis,</hi> as <hi>Athanaſius</hi> ſpake; Lord, how pitifully miſerable are they, whoſe eyes are thus ſhut up, as <hi>Eſay</hi> ſpeakes, as not to ſee that the ſtock is a doctrine of vanity, as <hi>Ieremie</hi> ſpeakes? but thus to magnifie idols, to cry out thus, <hi>Great Diana.</hi> And as this wood<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe lived thus among the heathen, would it had likewiſe dyed among the heathen too; and that what <hi>Tertullian</hi> bewail'd, <hi>Gentes agimus ſub nomine Chriſti,</hi> None un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the name of Chriſt thus playd the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then; that Painters and Bakers did not yet alſo furniſh them with gods, <hi>Et Faber &amp; Piſtor mille dedere deos:</hi> That as of old <hi>Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to</hi> gaue <hi>Dionyſius</hi> that for a privie token, that looke which of his Epiſtles hee begun with <hi>Deus</hi> ſingular, he ſhould take that to bee ſerious; but <hi>Dij</hi> pluralll, that to bee but light and trifling. As the multiplicity of idoll-mock-gods amongſt the heathen, ſo the pontificiall plurality of Images, call them what they will, makes mee often thinke many of them are not in earneſt, but onely in ieaſt with religion, and have
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:17662:66"/> thoſe puppets rather as play-fellowes, than as patrons, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>in dijs lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dentes, ſeipſos ludificantes,</hi> as <hi>Clemens</hi> ſpake, dallying with their gods, but deluding themſelves; for let both their Leeches ſalve over their actuall practices with ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culative plaiſters, let their Sophiſters mince the matter into nice differences, betweene <hi>Idola</hi> and <hi>Imagines, imagines</hi> and <hi>prototypa, propter imaginem,</hi> and <hi>coram imagine, ſimu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lachrum</hi> and <hi>in ſimulachro, Propriè</hi> and <hi>Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>propriè, Analogicè</hi> and <hi>Reductivè, Abſolutè</hi> and <hi>Reſpectivè,</hi> intention inſtrumentall and finall, and all that other; let them ſay with them in the ſecond of <hi>Ieremy,</hi> We are not polluted: Yet if they make not onely a creature, but even the image of a creature, partaker both of the power and worſhip of God; if they worſhip God miſconcei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, and offer up and worſhip a breaden Chriſt; if to the bleſſed <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>irgin</hi> they pray, and weepe, and crave, and beg even to the remiſsion of ſinnes; if they call upon their canoniz'd Saints both in private and pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique prayer; if they ſet images in their Churches, not onely <hi>ut conformemus, ſed ut colamus,</hi> as their own Catechiſme dictats:
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:17662:66"/> let the perſons cleare themſelves as they may, I meddle not with their perſons; all the water in Tyber will not cleanſe ſuch principles from pollution this way, ſeeing a man cannot partake, no not of the leaſt circumſtance of Idolatry, but it is (at leaſt) pollution unto him. And whether I plung into the depth of the ſea, or ſhallower near the ſhore, the drowning in both places is death vnto me: that as where the river is dangerous, a wiſe man will never walk ſo neare the brinke as hee may; Idolatrie that gulfe deep as hell, he that is wiſe unto ſalvation will not approach, no, not neare the confines of it: But (as Saint <hi>Iude</hi> bids) Hate even the garment ſpotted with the fleſh; hee will be ſhy even of the leaſt rag, the leaſt relique of it. Ignorant is hee that does not know, and ungratefull hee that does not acknowledge to the glory of God, the comfort of his Church, &amp; the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowne of this government, that whatever by-ditches or curtian lakes there bee, the ſtreame of our people now, the ſtreame runs cleare, not maddy'd with any filth of this heatheniſh harlotry. And yet to preſſe the deteſtation of it, the diſcourſe being
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:17662:67"/> both <hi>proponenda</hi> and <hi>inculcanda,</hi> as <hi>Tertulli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an</hi> ſpake about it, every where to bee ur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, the inclination to it being ſo naturall, the evaſion out of it ſo inextricable, the continuing in it ſo intolerable. When they choſe new gods, then was warre in the gates, <hi>Iudges</hi> 5. and not a ſpeare or ſhield ſeen among forty thouſand of them: they had then no heart to reſiſt the enemy. Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fring to another god their ſorrowes ſhall be multiplied, ſaies the 16. <hi>Pſalm.</hi> Babylon is fallen, is fallen, ſaid the Angel; a double fal for idolatrous Balylon. They have fallen culpably, and they ſhall fall penally. If a man would know the next way to hell, why ſurely along by <hi>Diana's</hi> doore, Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theniſh Idolatry: Idolaters not inheriting the kingdome of God, as S. <hi>Paul</hi> witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth: That unleſſe thou beeſt of his mind, who had rather have his part in Paris than Paradiſe; unleſſe of their clan in <hi>Eſay,</hi> who make covenant with death, and with hell are at agreement; unleſſe of their race, who run headlong to deſtruction; goe now a whoring thus after Idols, if thou dareſt: with more ſafetie mighteſt thou imbrace a firebrand; everie Idoll being the Idoll of
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:17662:67"/> indignation, as in <hi>Ezekiell:</hi> And woe unto him that ſaith unto the wood, Ariſe, and to the dumbeſtone Riſe up, as in <hi>Habakuk.</hi> They are curſed in <hi>Deuteronomy</hi> that make any graven or molten Image, and put it in a ſecret place: And the time will come when they too will curſe their gods, as in <hi>Eſay,</hi> when the Idolater, as one ſaid of <hi>Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian,</hi> ſhall burne in hell with that ſame wood and ſtone hee adoreth here. Call then unto thy Saints, if any will anſwere, and to which of thy goddeſſes wilt thou turne for helpe? Nay, behold all that are of the fellowſhip therof ſhall all of them be coufounded, as <hi>Eſay</hi> ſpeaketh. But yee that have not ſo learned Chriſt, to whom there is none other God but one, as <hi>Paul</hi> to the Corinthians; <hi>Anglia regnum Dei,</hi> as was ſaid of old, not <hi>Dianae;</hi> with <hi>Paul</hi> I charge you, before that God, and before the Lord Ieſus Chriſt, that ye never preſume thus to provoke the Lord to iealouſie, but ever perſever, perſiſt to caſt away all ſuch hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theniſh traſh, to ſay unto it, <hi>Apage, egredere,</hi> Away, get thee hence, as in <hi>Eſay:</hi> no hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie repentance being poſsible, with any af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection to Idolatry, as it is there wel noted.
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:17662:68"/> Here wee meete now frequently, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe our ſelves penitents; but heare me, If thou, whoſoever thou art, beeſt not in a ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gid oppoſition to all Idolatry, (to ſay no worſe) thou art in a remote indiſpoſition to repentance: and better thou wereſt out of this place than in it; for what agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment hath any Temple of God with I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dols? Into ſuch counſell never let your ſoules come; let never your glorie ioyne with ſuch aſſemblies; never change wee our honour for that which doth not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fite: minde we the great God, and we ſhal not thus magnifie any other; ſay we with <hi>Zorobabel,</hi> Truth's great, whilſt they ſay <hi>Great Diana;</hi>
               <q>Great is Diana of the Epheſians.</q>
            </p>
            <p>But as one well divided Idolatry, into I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolatry of opinion, and Idolatry of man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners; though theſe <hi>Diana's</hi> of opinion moſt of us (God be thanked) abandon, yet the <hi>Diana's</hi> of maners many of us abound with: every one with bowed knee wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipping the Idoll of his owne concupi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcence, and adoring the Image of his owne luſt, as <hi>Cyprian</hi> complained. <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> ſayes the Heathen made vicious affections
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:17662:68"/> gods we make even our vices our gods, that which every man loveth moſt, that being his god. He that prefers Luſt before God, makes luſt his god, and ſo of the reſt. <hi>Sua cuique Deus fit dira cupido:</hi> As <hi>Tertullian</hi> diſcourſes well all ſinnes to be in Idolatry, and Idolatry to be in everie ſinne; everie mans minion ſinne being his Idoll, everie mans darling deſire his <hi>Diana:</hi> For though thou doe not with the Heathen ſacrifice Oxen to it, yet offereſt thou to it thine owne ſoule for ſacrifice. Excellently ſayes <hi>Chriſoſtome;</hi> Though thou doeſt not adore it, yet doeſt thou obey it; though thou doeſt not carue its image, yet doeſt thou ſubmit to its inticements, making it thy deare <hi>Diana,</hi> and thy ſelfe an idolater in manners: as they ſay of <hi>Antipherus, Ante ſe idolum ſui,</hi> that whither ſoever he went, he thought his owne image went before him: reflecting all upon our ſelues; idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters either of our owne commoditie, cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſneſſe, as S. <hi>Paul</hi> ſayes, being idolatry, or idolaters of our owne ſenſualitie, whoſe god is their belly, Philipians the 3. or ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laters of our owne pride, to the ſetting out of which Idoll, goe gold, and ſilver, and
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:17662:69"/> blew ſilke and purple, as in <hi>Ieremy;</hi> or of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther manifeſt works of the fleſh, amongſt which <hi>Paul</hi> reckons idolatry; or more cloſe idolaters of our credit, as one ſpake well, or idolaters of our diſcretion, or ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laters of our abilities, <hi>idolum in nobis ipſis ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citantes,</hi> as he ſpake; ſetting vp an idoll in our hearts, as in <hi>Ezekiel.</hi> Idolaters of cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony, as one calls Courtiers: idolaters of others greatneſſe; hoping to bee made by them, as they ſpeake, they become ſuch or ſuch a great ones creature, as they ſay, <hi>nec tam praeſentes alibi cognoſcere divos.</hi> And in the winding vp, what comes all this and that idolatry too? why ſurely as 'tis well noted, that this ſame <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, plurality of gods, firſt came from fluctuation of mind, the vnſettled mind ſeeking god after god, and finding none to reſt in, but adding drunkenneſſe to thirſt, as <hi>Moſes</hi> ſpake. As fluctuation of minde ſo bred it, ſo what does it breed now but fluctuation of minde? all theſe vaine idols of our idle va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities affoording our minds no true con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent, ſweet reſt, no ſound ſatisfaction; in them we labouring for that which ſatisfi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth not, as <hi>Eſay</hi> ſayes. He that loveth ſilver,
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:17662:69"/> ſaith <hi>Salomon;</hi> and ſo with all other idols: He that loveth ſilver, ſhall not be ſatisfied with it, Eccleſ. 5. onely to behold Gods face in righteouſneſſe, that ſatisfieth: I ſhal be ſatisfied with thine image, ſayes <hi>Dauid;</hi> not ſo with all thoſe idols: There is ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction in the pleaſure of thine houſe, as <hi>Dauid</hi> ſpeakes; there is not ſo in any thoſe idols: <hi>Tu ſatis es nobis &amp; ſine te nihil eſt:</hi> that wouldſt thou haue true tranquility and peace of mind? why then returne O my ſoule vnto thy reſt, the Lord. The very letters in <hi>Iehovah</hi> are all <hi>quieſcent:</hi> thy heart was made for the true God; nor can it quiet be, untill it reſt in him: he onely be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>centrum quietativum,</hi> the center of the ſoule, wherein alone it findeth reſt. The heart, a little member, that will not ſerue a Kite for a meale, as one ſpake, and yet aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much as the Kite flyes over, all the world will not ſerue it: as little as it is, nothing leſſe than God can ſuffice it. The great God can fill it, ſo can no great <hi>Diana,</hi> 
               <q>Great is Diana of the Epheſians.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Great?</hi> happely great in the eyes of ſome ſilly people, who if they ſee any thing gay, tis ſtreight with them great: If a man, as
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:17662:70"/> Saint <hi>Iames</hi> ſpeakes, come in with a gold ring or gay clothing, Great is too little for him in the mouth of gazing men, who though he be not <hi>optimus,</hi> they'le make him <hi>maximus,</hi> if they cannot make him good, they'le make him great: No but theſe fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes here were not every body, but <hi>Ephe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſians,</hi> the infection of Idolatry being ſo ſmittle, that as the former verſe mentions, all Aſia, and the world worſhipping her, <hi>Diana</hi> had got footing in moſt Nations; a fountaine had ſhe in Sicilie, a haven in Sardinia, a wood in Venetia, an oracle in Apabia, temples in Eubaea, Achaia, Archadia, and more than is meete here to name: but above all, the famous temple at Epheſus; as that he that would ſee <hi>Diana</hi> in her holy-day cloth, finde her in her court-dreſsings, her faireſt equipage and capariſons, hee muſt looke for her a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong <hi>Epheſians, Great Diana of Epheſians:</hi> thats the laſt part. <hi>Ephſians?</hi> why what were they? why no obſcure Ruſticks, but of the famous City Epheſus, that light of Aſia, as it is called, the metropolis of Aſia <hi>minor,</hi> whither all thoſe parts then fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently reſorted, either for Religions ſake,
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:17662:70"/> as having there the Temple, or for buſines, as being then the Metropolis, or for ſtudy, as being then the Vniverſity, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, ſaies <hi>Philoſtratus</hi> of it, abounding with Philoſophers, Orators, and the like, <hi>Pytha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goras, Parmenides, Democritus,</hi> and the reſt, renowned for choiſe men and much wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, ſaies <hi>Philoſtratus:</hi> Inſomuch, that <hi>Suidas</hi> telling how the prophane Graecians wont to couſen the ſimple people, by either baniſhing or killing the ſtatuary, and then giving out, as herein the context, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, that the image came downe from <hi>Iupiter</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, ſaies <hi>Suidas</hi> there, with an Emphaſis, the trick deceived the very <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſians:</hi> men ſo intelligent as not likely to be ſo deluded. And yet for all that learning, skil &amp; abilities, behold here Epheſus even a ſtews of Idolatry, above all other their vitioſity, behold here how the witchcraft of Idolatry ſo beſots and befooles them, otherwiſe wiſe in their generation, as all of them, as followes in the context to cry, town clark and all to ſay, <hi>Great Diana.</hi> That as they in S. <hi>Proſper</hi> boaſted the meliority of the wits of thoſe times, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond the ancient; wherefore boaſt any
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:17662:71"/> people ſo of their wits, and learning, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilities, as if theſe were immunities from erring? whereas, in truth, that poſition condemn'd at Paris, That the better natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralls muſt of neceſsity have the greater grace, is ſo farre from truth, as that often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times men truſting and tranſported with thoſe their good parts, as they call them, undervalue grace, and ſo thoſe their parts ſo abuſed, prove rather unto them as preſſe-money to impiety: <hi>Auctoramentum maioris infidelitatis,</hi> as he well phraſeth it; and their wiſedome <hi>Culpae ſuaſoria,</hi> as <hi>Ambroſe</hi> ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth; that though, as <hi>Paul</hi> ſpake, If any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther man thinketh that hee hath whereof hee might truſt in the fleſh, much more I: if any people may now boaſt abilities, we more; yet let not that ſecure us from fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling into errour, but watch and pray, that we enter not into temptation, that we be not overcome of evill, that wee never cry with <hi>Epheſians, Great Diana.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That not to wander out of the way, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides and beyond that Idolatrous inclina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of <hi>Epheſians</hi> in generall, crying out in the context; theſe crying <hi>Epheſians</hi> here in the Text, had a more particular intereſt
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:17662:71"/> in her, that made her thus great to them; a certaine thing called gaine: for though in the ſound of their cry they mention onely <hi>Diana,</hi> yet in the cauſe of their cry, the verſes mixes other ingredients of their trade, yea, the ſpirit by order of enumera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, ſeemes to point that out, for the prime and principall motive in their cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. The feare of loſing their commings in, caus'd them ſo to cry out, &amp; made them ſo cry <hi>Great Diana.</hi> As Logicians well can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaſſe the cauſes, the procatarcticall cauſe of their cry was, forſooth, Piety, the proegu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menall cauſe was commodity; their por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, as themſelves calld it, their profit. In the cry <hi>Diana</hi> bears all the name, but in the cryers there was a falfe aime, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, againe and again in the context here, our wealth, and our portion; looking ſo through the ſpectacles of ſelfe intereſt, this made her ſhew ſo great to them, made them cry <hi>Great Diana.</hi> Like Lap-wings crying aloof from their neſt, the cry runs upon their goddeſſe, but the neſt lay in their gaine; as they made ſhrines for <hi>Diana,</hi> ſo making skreekes of <hi>Diana</hi> too, ſtauking to their ends of gaine, under the ſhadow of their
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:17662:72"/> goddeſſe; theſe craftſmen, were their crafts maſters, <hi>dolus in idolo,</hi> pretending godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, intending gaine, they did beſtow di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinity on that which brought commodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty: they gain'd greatly by <hi>Diana,</hi> therefore cryd they, <hi>Great is Diana.</hi> So true is that <hi>Tertullian</hi> ſpake of the heathen, <hi>Non licet deos noſſe gratis, &amp;c.</hi> they made a gaine of their gods, that though their gods were nought, they did not ſerve them for nought. Idolatry being not <hi>gratuita,</hi> ſaies hee, not ſerving God for god a mercy, but <hi>captatrix,</hi> ſaies <hi>Rhenanus,</hi> lying at catch for commodity: ſo common is that of <hi>Epicte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>ubi utilitas, ibi pietas,</hi> it is the profit that keeps up the pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty: ſo well ſaid the heathen man <hi>deos quiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que ſibi utiles cudit,</hi> men love to coyn them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves commodious gods; with them in the 44. of <hi>Ieremy,</hi> to incenſe to the Queen of heaven for plenties ſake, to meaſure Religion by the belly, to magnifie thus that whereby their portion is made fat and their meate plenteous, as the Prophet ſpeaketh. That whereas beſides that Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>net of the Fathers, Idolatry to have come firſt from the devill, as <hi>Clemens</hi> ſaies, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:17662:72"/> as <hi>Epiphanius;</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, as <hi>Syneſius</hi> call him, as reioycing in Idols. Some hold griefe to have beene the firſt founder of I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dols, <hi>Idolum Idodynin,</hi> as <hi>Fulgentius</hi> fetches it from <hi>Syrophanes:</hi> and others hold feare to have founded, <hi>Primus in orbe deos fecit timor:</hi> and I encline to thinke they firſt ſprung from flattery. It may probably bee thought, gainefull intereſt was the firſt founder of them, eſpecially among the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maniſts: <hi>Qui Pietatem quaeſtum, Religionem praedam, exiſtimant,</hi> as <hi>Aventinus</hi> ſpoke of them, They count gaine Godlineſſe, and make Religion their prey, making thus ſhew of Religion, when their aime is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venew; with theſe ſilvet ſmiths here, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging moſt of their gaine thus upon the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vile of <hi>Diana.</hi> For in this haſt to paſſe by their ſophiſticall gaines by the Lady of the lake, and the like, and worſe; in paſſage caſt but your eye upon their doctrinall <hi>Diana's;</hi> their <hi>Diana</hi> of purgatory, doe ye any think, they thinke it a point of truth, or not only thus of traffique and profit? Purgatory pickpurſe having fire to no other end, ſave onely to make their pot boile, and their kitchins ſmooke: ſo their <hi>Diana</hi> of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſsion,
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:17662:73"/> as they abuſe it, is it not become the engine, whereby (as is well noted) they firſt dive into mens conſciences and coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſells, and afterwards into their purſes and eſtates by abſolution? Their <hi>Diana's</hi> of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgences, are they (trow ye) miſtreſſes of piety, or are they not matters of the mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ket-houſe, plaine penny worths rather? I would not weary you with their foule waies, nor ſully this preſence with any foule relations, howbeit foule: moſt foule was that blaſphemy of their <hi>Caiphas</hi> to his Cardinall, that that ſame fable of Chriſt had beene very profitable to him; much more be their owne deviſes never ſo fabu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous, yet ſo long as they are commodious, all is well may yee thinke. That as <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broſe</hi> ſpake of <hi>Beniamins</hi> ſack, <hi>ſacco ſoluto apparuit argentum,</hi> that when the ſack was looſed the ſilver appeared, reſolve much of their Theology, into that whereof tis con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituted, and ſilver will appeare, commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dity will be found to be the chiefe element of conſtitution: and that becauſe unleſſe their <hi>Diana's</hi> bee held up, their commodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties would downe; therfore cry they thus, <hi>Great Diana.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="139" facs="tcp:17662:73"/>
            <p>And O that none of this <hi>Epheſian</hi> leaven were now to bee found here amongſt our ſelves alſo, who as it is reprehended in <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer,</hi> that mingling gods with men, hee ſpake great things of the men, but meane things of the gods, wee moſt of us ſo min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle religion with worldly ends, as that there is in us ſuch a great deale of the one, but ſo little of the other, that as tis ſaid of the <hi>Scythians,</hi> that they once ſmootherd their gods with earth, many of us ſeeme almoſt to have ſmootherd our godlineſſe with our worldlineſſe, retaining onely <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, not <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, as <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeakes, not the power of godlineſſe, but onely the forme thereof, to further our other purpoſes: much like the fellow, who vowing to <hi>Mercury</hi> halfe of what he found, finding almonds, preſented onely the ſhells upon the altar; If we affoord God a ſhell in Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, it is to get the kirnells to our ſelves, following Chriſt more for his bread than his doctrine; in our thoughts putting <hi>pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem noſtrum,</hi> before <hi>nomen tuum;</hi> making pretence of piety, pandar to profit, lending little to Religion but ſuch offices as may broke for our other ends, ſuch paſſages as
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:17662:74"/> may bee factors for our profit, ſhuffling in Religion, onely to deale our ſelves a win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning game, making profeſsing of Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on only profits ſtirrop to get up by, making ſhew of ſerving God onely to ſerve our owne turnes. As the winde changing, the weather altereth; upon any alteration rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to turne, and returne, and overturne, as may beſt ſerve our turne, to make our mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ket, under ſome mask of devotion; eying thus co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>modity, though crying thus <hi>Diana.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But be not deceived, God is not mocked. As let never intereſt, no not of life make you leane to falſe worſhip, ſo let never end of gaine, make you feigne either falſe or true worſhip: for whats the hope of the Hypocrite, though he hath gained? To cry thus <hi>Diana,</hi> Religion, and in the mean time to care only for commodity, &amp; com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mings in, will one day make all that gaine, as gravell in thy mouth, as the Prophet <hi>Micah</hi> ſpake: that which is gathred of the hire of an harlot, ſhall return to the wages of an harlot, that thus falſly gotten, ſhall be as fowly gone: that though with <hi>Paul,</hi> yee wil put on faith as a breſtplate, yet never put yee on Religion as a cloak, but ſay we
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:17662:74"/> ſincerely, Great is the myſtery of godlineſs, whilſt theſe ſophiſtically cry,
<q>Great is Diana of the Epheſians.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Yea, for concluſion, this ſame <hi>Epheſus</hi> of all other (as tis noted) eſpecially ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowing forth the Church of the Gentils; All yee that heare mee this day, at parting now looke well upon theſe <hi>Epheſians,</hi> and what ſee you them here? why Idolatrous. Look forward into the <hi>Revelation:</hi> why religious. Look down upon them at this day, and what ſee you them now? why mahumetically miſerable: And ſeeing it ſo in them, reflect the ſight homeward upon our ſelves, who had a time likewiſe of I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolatry, have a time likewiſe of ſincerity, pray we, we never have a time likewiſe of miſery, that it never come to paſſe with England, which was threatned and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed to <hi>Epheſus, I will come againſt thee ſhortly, and remove thy Candleſticke out of his place, except thou amend:</hi> yea, <hi>Amend your lives for the Kingdome of God is at hand: &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
